<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../OLAC_doc.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "../OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc> 
   <header>
      <status code="draft" type="recommendation"/>
      <title>Best Practice Recommendations for Language Resource
         Description</title>
      <baseName>bpr</baseName>
      <issued>20070924</issued>
      <previousIssued/>
      <abstract>
         <p>This document expresses the consensus of the Open Language
            Archives Community on best practice recommendations for
            language resource description using the OLAC metadata standard
         <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>.</p>
      </abstract>
      <editors>Gary Simons, SIL International
            (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>)<br/>Steven Bird,
         University of Pennsylvania
         (<url>mailto:sb@ldc.upenn.edu</url>)</editors>
      <copyright>2007 Gary Simons (SIL International) and Steven Bird
         (University of Pennsylvania)</copyright>

      <changes/>
   </header> 
   <body>

      <section>
         <heading>Introduction</heading>
         <p>This document expresses the consensus of the Open Language
            Archives Community on best practices for describing
            language resources using the OLAC metadata standard
            <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>. The standard itself specifies the formal constraints
            on the syntax of valid descriptions, but does not set requirements on the
            content of the metadata elements (beyond general conformance to the definitions
            of the qualified Dublin Core metadata set <cit>DCMI</cit>). This document
            provides more detailed guidance about the content of specific metadata
            elements.</p>
         <p>This document does not provide a complete set of advice about what the
            metadata elements means and how they are to be used. Such advice is supplied
            in an OLAC informational note <cit>OLAC-Usage</cit>. This document lists only
            specific metadata usage guidelines that have been agreed upon by the OLAC community as
            representing best practice.  It is not a requirement of participation that OLAC data providers
            follow these recommendations. However, these recommendations will be used as the standard for
            evaluating the quality of the metadata records supplied by an OLAC data
            provider. </p></section>
      <section>
         <heading>Recommendations from 2002</heading>
         <p>This section is temporary.  It is holding the recommendations written in the
            2002 version of the document.  The next section shows the recommendations that
         are being automatically copied in from NOTE/usage.xml. The current section will be
         deleted once we have decided that we don't need the information any more. </p>
         <p>The recommendations are listed below under the metadata
            element they pertain to.</p>

         <subsection>
            <subheading>All elements</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Whenever the language of the element content is
                     other than English, recommended best practice is
                     to use the <i>lang</i> attribute to identify the
                     language.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Contributor, Creator, Publisher</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Recommended best practice is to identify the
                     entity by means of a name and to give the name in
                     a form that is ready for sorting within an index.
                     For the names of persons, this means that the
                     name should be given in inverted order with the
                     surname first. For the names of organizations,
                     this means that any initial article should be
                     omitted. </p>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <p>When a resource has more than one contributor,
                     creator, or publisher, use a separate
                     Contributor, Creator, or Publisher element for
                     each one.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Date</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Recommended best practice is to use a coded value
                     when possible, since that guarantees that a
                     service provider can do a straight alphanumeric
                     sort to put collections of metadata descriptions
                     in correct chronological order.</p>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <p>The encoded value may match one of the four
                     following patterns: <tt>YYYY</tt>,
                     <tt>YYYY-MM</tt>, <tt>YYYY-MM-DD</tt>, or
                        <tt>YYYY-YYYY</tt>.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Format</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>The <i>code</i> attribute should be used to make
                     a precise identification of the format using a
                     controlled vocabulary. This is especially
                     important for digital resources since service
                     providers may use this information to match data
                     resources with the software tools that are
                     appropriate for manipulating them.</p>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <p>[The OLAC-Format vocabulary was not elaborated,
                     but it was suggested that it should be based on
                        <cit>MIME</cit> types.]</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Format.markup</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Recommended best practice is to identify the
                     markup scheme by a URI giving an OAI identifier
                     for the markup scheme as a resource in an OLAC
                     archive. Thus, if the DTD, Schema, or markup
                     documentation is not already archived in an OLAC
                     repository, the depositor of a marked-up resource
                     should also deposit the documentation for the
                     markup scheme. </p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Identifier</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Recommended best practice is to identify the
                     resource by means of a string or number
                     conforming to a globally-known formal
                     identification system. Example formal
                     identification systems include the Uniform
                     Resource Identifier (URI) (including the Uniform
                     Resource Locator (URL)), the Digital Object
                     Identifier (DOI), and the International Standard
                     Book Number (ISBN).</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Language, Subject.language</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Recommended best practice is to specify the
                     language via the <i>code</i> attribute while
                     leaving the element content empty. </p>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <p>Use the element content only when the controlled
                     vocabulary does not offer an appropriate code, or
                     when further specification is needed, such as to
                     name a specific dialect or to give an alternate
                     name that differs from the default name given by
                     the controlled vocabulary.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Source</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Recommended best practice for OLAC is to reserve
                     the use of Source for cases when the present
                     resource has a substantially different Type or
                     Creator or Title than the Source resource. </p>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <p>When the difference from the original work is
                     only a difference of Date or Format or Publisher
                     or Identifier or edition designator in the Title,
                     then use Relation to encode the relationship to
                     the original work.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Subject</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Recommended best practice is to select a value
                     from a controlled vocabulary or formal
                     classification scheme. The <i>scheme</i>
                     attribute is used to identify the scheme.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Title</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>When there is more than one instance of Title,
                     recommended best practice is that only one
                     instance, namely the original title, be
                     unqualified. All others (e.g. translations)
                     should specify <tt>code="alternative"</tt>.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Type</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Recommended best practice is to use the
                     <i>code</i> attribute to identify the type using
                     the Dublin Core Types controlled vocabulary
                        <cit>DC-Type</cit>. The element content is
                     typically left empty. Use the element content
                     only when the controlled vocabulary does not
                     offer an appropriate type, or when further
                     specification is needed.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Type.functionality</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Recommended best practice is to the <i>code</i>
                     attribute to identify the software functionality
                     using a controlled vocabulary. See
                     OLAC-Functionality for the definition of the
                     vocabulary.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection>
            <subheading>Type.linguistic</subheading>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Recommended best practice is to the <i>code</i>
                     attribute to identify the linguistic data type
                     using a controlled vocabulary. See
                     OLAC-Linguistic-Type for the definition of the
                     vocabulary.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
         </subsection>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>Recommendations</heading>
         <p>These are the recommendations automatically copied from the NOTE/usage.xml.</p>
         <recommendations href="../NOTE/usage.xml"/>
      </section>
      
      
   </body> 
   
  <references> 
    
     <ref abbrev="DCMI">DCMI Metadata Terms.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/</url>&gt;</ref>
    
     <ref abbrev="OLAC-Metadata">OLAC Metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url>&gt;</ref>
     
     <ref abbrev="OLAC-Usage">OLAC Metadata Usage
        Guidelines.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/NOTE/usage.html</url>&gt;</ref>
     
  </references>
</OLAC_doc>
