<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../OLAC_doc.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "../OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc>
   <header>
      <status code="draft" type="informational"/>
      <title>OLAC Metadata Usage Guidelines</title>
      <baseName>usage</baseName>
      <issued>20071018</issued>
      <previousIssued/>
      <abstract>
         <p>This document provides guidelines on the meaning and proper usage of the
            metadata elements used in the metadata standard of the Open Language Archives
            Community.</p>
      </abstract>
      <editors>Gary Simons, SIL International
         (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>)<br/>Steven Bird, University of
         Pennsylvania (<url>mailto:sb@ldc.upenn.edu</url>)</editors>
      <copyright>2007 Gary Simons (SIL International) and Steven Bird (University of
         Pennsylvania)</copyright>
      <changes/>
   </header>
   <body>
      <section>
         <heading>Introduction</heading>
         <p>This document provides guidelines on how to describe language resources using
            the OLAC metadata standard <cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>. The standard itself
            documents the formal syntax of valid metadata records, but does not explain or
            exemplify the use of the individual metadata elements. That is the purpose of
            this document. </p>
         <p>Section 2 below describes the usage of the attributes that may be used on
            metadata elements. Section 3 then describes usage in the OLAC context for the
            fifteen core elements of the Dublin Core metadata set. Section 4 describes
            other elements that may be used..</p>
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>All elements</heading>
         <p>Four attributes&#8212;<i>refine, code, scheme,</i> and
            <i>lang</i>&#8212;are used throughout the XML implementation of the
            metadata elements. A fifth attribute, <i>langs,</i> is used on complete
            metadata records. These are described in turn below.</p>
         <p> Some elements in the OLAC metadata set use the <i>refine</i> attribute to
            identify element refinements. These qualifiers make the meaning of an element
            narrower or more specific. A refined element shares the meaning of the
            unqualified element, but with a more restricted scope <cit>DC-Q</cit>. When an
            element does use a <i>refine</i> attribute, the possible values for the
            attribute are restricted to a specified controlled vocabulary.</p>
         <p>Some elements in the OLAC metadata set use the <i>code</i> attribute to hold
            metadata values that are taken from a specific encoding scheme. The attribute
            value is always a precise value taken from a controlled vocabulary or a formal
            notation that is described in another OLAC document. As a result, all service
            providers are able to interpret uniformly the meaning of any <i>code</i>
            value. The terms of a controlled vocabulary are also incorporated into the XML
            schema for OLAC metadata; thus every <i>code</i> value is tested for validity
            when the OLAC registration server tests a data provider for conformance to
            OLAC standards <cit>OLAC-Registration</cit>. For elements that have a
            <i>code</i> attribute, the element content may also be used to specify a
            freeform elaboration of the coded value.</p>
         <p>Every element in the OLAC metadata set may use the <i>scheme</i> attribute. It
            specifies a standardized name for the scheme that constrains how the text in
            the content of the element is encoded. A scheme may be a controlled vocabulary
            or a formal notation. Recommended best practice is to confine the value of
               <i>scheme</i> to the label for one of the encoding schemes registered with
            the Dublin Core Metadata Initiative <cit>DCMI-Registry</cit>. Members of the
            OLAC community who want to use an unregistered scheme should submit it for
            registration <cit>DCMI-Submit</cit>. When OLAC data providers are tested for
            conformance to OLAC recommended best practice, only the value of the
            <i>scheme</i> attribute is tested for inclusion in the list of registered
            schemes. OLAC does not test the actual element content for conformance to the
            scheme; a service provider for a subcommunity that has developed a particular
            scheme could perform such a test. </p>
         <p>Every element in the OLAC metadata set may use the <i>lang</i> attribute. It
            specifies the language in which the text in the content of the element is
            written. The value for the attribute comes from the controlled vocabulary
            defined by <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>. By default, the <i>lang</i> attribute has
            the value "en", for English. Whenever the language of the element content is
            other than English, recommended best practice is to use the <i>lang</i>
            attribute to identify the language. By using multiple instances of the
            metadata elements tagged for different languages, data providers may offer
            their metadata records in multiple languages. </p>
         <p>The <i>langs</i> attribute is used on the <tt>&lt;olac&gt;</tt>
            element&#8212;the container for all the metadata elements of a given
            metadata record. It lists the languages in which the metadata record is
            designed to be read. This attribute holds a space-delimited list of language
            codes from the <cit>OLAC-Language</cit> controlled vocabulary. By default,
            this attribute has the value "en", for English, indicating that the record is
            aimed only at English readers. If an explicit value is given for the
            attribute, then the record is aimed at readers of all the languages listed.</p>
         <p>Service providers should use this information in order to offer localized
            views of the metadata. When a metadata record lists only one language, then
            all elements should be displayed (regardless of their individual languages),
            unless the user has requested to suppress all records in that language. When a
            metadata record has multiple alternative languages, the user should be able to
            select one and have display of elements in the other languages suppressed. An
            element in a language not included in the list of alternatives should always
            be displayed (for instance, the vernacular title of a work).</p>
         <p>In a given metadata record, every element is optional and every element is
            repeatable.</p>
         <element name="All elements">
            <definition><!-- Don't use. Just a trick to make export to RED/bpr.xml work. --></definition>
            <comment><!-- Ditto. --></comment>
            <bp>
               <p>Minimal best practice is for the value of each metadata element to
               conform to the definition of that element.</p>
               <p>When the meaning of a particular element in a metadata record fits the
                  definition of a refinement, recommended best practice is to use the
                  refinement rather than the generic element.</p>
               <p>Whenever the language of the element content is
                  other than English, recommended best practice is
                  to use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute with a value from <cit>ISO639-3</cit> to identify the
                  language.</p>
               <p>When a resource has more than one value for a particular metadata
                  element, recommended best practice is to use a separate instance of the
                  metadata element for each instance rather than listing all the values in
                  a single instance.</p>
            </bp>
            <examples><!-- I think we want to put these here --></examples>
         </element>
         
      </section>
      <section>
         <heading>Individual elements</heading>
         <p>Each of the core elements of the Dublin Core metadata set is described in one of the following
            subsections. The heading gives the name of the
            element; the element is then described under six subheadings.
            <i>Definition</i> is the definition for the element as given by the Dublin
            Core Metadata Initiative <cit>DCMT</cit>.
            <i>Refinements</i> lists the refined element names (from the <i>dcterms</i>
            namespace) that may be used in place of the generic element name to specify a
            more precise meaning for the metadata item. The refinement definitions are copied from  <cit>DCMT</cit>.
            <i>Schemes</i> lists the encoding schemes that may be used with this element
            (or its refinements) as the value of the <i>xsi:type</i> attribute.
            <i>Best practices</i> lists the best practices for the use of this element
            that are recommended by the OLAC community <cit>OLAC-BP</cit>. 
            <i>Usage notes</i> offers additional notes for the OLAC community
            on how to use the element in the context of describing language resources. 
            <i>Examples</i> shows samples of
            properly encoded elements and sample refinements.</p>
      	<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
      	<p>While the order of the elements is not specified in the OLAC standard, maintaining the proper order of the markers as defined in the database type definition is essential to the proper operation of the XML and XSL processes down the line.</p>
      	<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
      	<p>For many elements, you can have more than one instance. This would be the case for a work with more than one author, or for which you want to specify two or three languages, multiple subject terms, etc. In such cases, repeat the element for each person, language, etc., rather than placing all of them in a single instance of the field. Most elements can be repeated if needed.</p>
      	<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
      	<p>Other fields also have optional sub-elements, the most common of which is a *Lang element, used to specify the language used in the text of the element where it differs from the default language specified in the \md-lang field (metadata default language, usually “en”). For instance, you may wish to give both an English description and a Spanish description for a work, making a second \description element for the Spanish description, and entering  spa in its \descLang sub-element.</p>
      	<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
      	<p>The template is a very useful means of not only getting the right fields in the record, but also entering default data into a record where that data is common to many records...It is then a good strategy to work through your materials by grouping them as to shared metadata values. Good candidates for entering default data directly in the template might be:
      		•	Creator and possibly its sub-elements
      		•	Language and language code
      		•	Subject_language and subject_languageCode
      		•	Subject_linguistic-field (e.g., all language texts should have “language_documentation” in this field)
      		•	Type_linguistic-type (e.g., all language texts should have “language_text” in this field )
      		•	Type (e.g., all written language texts should have “text” in this field; all recordings of texts should have “sound” in this field.)
      		•	Medium +/- format
      	</p>
      	<element name="Contributor">
         	<definition>An entity responsible for making contributions to the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>A Contributor may be a person, an organization, or a service.
                  Contributor is closely related to <xref>Creator</xref>. The difference
                  has to do with degree of responsibility for the content. The Contributor
                  designation is used for those entities whose role in the creation of the
                  resource is not great enough to merit recognition as a primary source of
                  the intellectual content. This element may be used to identify
                  institutions that sponsored or funded the work. It may be used to
                  identify individuals who played a secondary role in the development of
                  the resource. As a rule of thumb, Creator is used when the contribution
                  is such that it would be cited in the "author" field of a bibliographic
                  entry, and Contributor is used otherwise.</p>
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>olac:role</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The <i>refine</i> attribute is optionally used to specify the role
                        (such as transcriber, sponsor, and so on) played by the named
                        entity in the creation of the resource. The role is expressed by
                        means of a controlled vocabulary; see <cit>OLAC-Role</cit> for the
                        definition of the vocabulary. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
           <bp>
           	<p>Recommended best practice is to identify the entity by means of a name
           	       in a form that is ready for sorting within an
           		index. For the names of persons, this means that the name should be
           		given in inverted order with the surname first. For the names of
           		organizations, this means that any initial article should be omitted.
           		</p>
              <p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>olac:role</i> scheme to
              indicate the role of the contributor.</p>
           	<p>Enter one name per element instance. Do not enter multiple names in single element instance. <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
           	<p>Use surname, firstname order; Main unit, subunit order to make the form of name entry ready for sort. <!-- 
           	http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
           	<p>Do not use quotation marks to enclose corporate names.  If the name is a translation from its usual form
           		or not usually given in English, use the lang attribute.  <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --><!-- need examples; the examples on slide were unclear - "Institute for Slovene Language ""Fran Ramovs"",
           			Slovene Academy for Sciences and Arts,
           			Ljubljana, Slovenia". --></p>
           	<p>Be consistent with corporate name forms. <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
           </bp>
         	<examples>
               <p>A generic contributor:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor&gt;Smith, John L.&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
               <p>A funding agency:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="sponsor"&gt;National 
   Science Foundation&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
               <p>The person who performed a role for which there is not a suitable code:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:contributor&gt;Smith, John L. (format conversion)&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Coverage">
         	<definition>The spatial or temporal topic of the resource, the spatial applicability of the resource, or the jurisdiction under which the resource is relevant.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p> Coverage will typically include spatial location (a place name or
                  geographic coordinates), temporal period (a period label, date, or date
                  range) or jurisdiction (such as a named administrative entity).
                     <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
            	<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->  
            	<p>Typically it can contain a country or region to which the resource relates.</p>
               <p>In the OLAC context, service providers already have a database that maps
                  languages to the countries in which they are spoken
                  <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>. Coverage should not be used to duplicate this
                  information; rather service providers will support searches concerning
                  languages spoken in a given country by referring to the language
                  database. Coverage should be used geographically only when the language
                  involved has a wide distribution and the resource focuses on its use in
                  a particular region or geopolitical jurisdiction, or conversely, when
                  the resource deals with a region that encompasses multiple languages.
               </p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>spatial</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Spatial characteristics of the intellectual content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>temporal</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Temporal characteristics of the intellectual content of the resource.Temporal characteristics of the intellectual content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:Box</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The DCMI Box identifies a region of space using its geographic
                  	   limits <cit>DCMI-Box</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:Point</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The DCMI Point identifies a point in space using its geographic
                  	   coordinates <cit>DCMI-Point</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dcterms:TGN</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names <cit>TGN</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
         	<bp>
         		<p>In the case of Spatial coverage, recommended best practice is to use an
         		   encoding scheme to give precise geocoding of the resource.</p>
            </bp>
         	
         	
            <examples>
               <p>A resource about English in India:</p>
            	<eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639" olac:code="en"/&gt;
&lt;dcterms:spatial&gt;India&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource about languages spoken on Guadalcanal:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:TGN"&gt;Guadalcanal (island)&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource about language use in the 19th century:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:temporal&gt;19th century&lt;/dcterms:temporal&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Creator">
         	<definition>An entity primarily responsible for making the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>A Creator may be a person, an organization, or a service. Creator is
                  closely related to <xref>Contributor</xref>. In determining whether an
                  entity is a Creator (as opposed to a Contributor), use the same criteria
                  that are followed for deciding that an entity should be listed in the
                  "author" slot of a bibliographic reference as a primary source of the
                  intellectual content. Entities that do not merit that level of
                  recognition should be treated as Contributors.</p>
               <!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
               <p>If western name, enter as Family-name, Given-name(s). If romanized form of Asian name where the family name is the common form of address, enter as Family-name Given-Name(s) without the comma.</p>
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>olac:role</dt>
               	<dd>
                     <p>The <i>refine</i> attribute is optionally used to specify the role
                        (such as author, editor, translator, and so on) played by the
                        named entity in the creation of the resource. The role is
                        expressed by means of a controlled vocabulary; see
                        <cit>OLAC-Role</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
           <bp>
           	<p>Recommended best practice is to identify a Creator by means of a name
           	   in a form that is ready for sorting within an
           		index. For the names of persons, this means that the name should be
           		given in inverted order with the surname first. For the names of
           		organizations, this means that any initial article should be omitted.
           		</p>
              <p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>olac:role</i> scheme to
              indicate the role of the contributor.</p>
           	<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
           	<p>For more than one author, repeat the \creator element and also its \creator_role sub-element.</p>
           	<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
           	<p>With texts authored or spoken by informants where there was no explicit agreement regarding how they would be used (for research, shared with other researchers, eventually published, etc.), the creators’ and participants’ names will be omitted from metadata made public for search purposes, and careful attention to preserving privacy—or expressing appropriate authorial credit—will be given whenever materials are made available upon request.</p>
           </bp>
         	
         	<examples>
               <p>A personal author:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:creator&gt;Bloomfield, Leonard&lt;/dc:creator&gt;</eg>
               <p>An institutional author:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:creator&gt;Linguistic Society of America&lt;/dc:creator&gt;</eg>
               <p>An editor:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:creator xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="editor"&gt;Sapir,
   Edward&lt;/dc:creator&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
            <todo>
               <p>Here, and with Contributor, we recommend a format that puts surname
                  first. Are there other name-related standards in AACR2 that we should
                  recommend? We need help from a librarian
                  to give us a synopsis (or a pointer to such) of the rules for fomatting
                  personal and corporate names. </p>
            </todo>
         </element>
         <element name="Date">
         	<definition>A point or period of time associated with an event in the lifecycle of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>The <i>code</i> attribute is used to hold a standardized encoding
                  of a date. Following <cit>DCMT</cit>, OLAC uses the YYYY-MM-DD
                  format as defined in <cit>W3CDTF</cit>. When a month or day value
                  is less than 10, use a leading 0 to maintain a two-digit length.
                  The encoded value may be for the year alone, for the year and
                  month, or for an exact date. A range of years is also a valid
                  value for this attribute; in this case both years must be
                  four-digit values and the earliest year should come first. Thus,
                  the encoded value may match one of the four following patterns:
                  <tt>YYYY</tt>, <tt>YYYY-MM</tt>, <tt>YYYY-MM-DD</tt>, or
                  <tt>YYYY-YYYY</tt>.</p>
               <p>A Date with no refinement will be assumed to be the date of issue
                  (i.e. publication). A single resource should not have more than
                  one instance of each date refinement. In selecting a single date
                  to associate with a resource, a service provider will select the
                  most recent of date created, issued, or modified.</p>
            	<p>date of publication may differ from its creation date)</p>
            	<p>- ‘Available’ as a refinement pertains to Date, not
            		to other aspects of availability <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf -->
            	</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>available</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Date (often a range) that the resource will become or did become available.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>created</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Date of creation of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dateAccepted</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Date of acceptance of the resource (e.g. of thesis by university department, of article by journal, etc.).</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dateCopyrighted</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Date of a statement of copyright.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>dateSubmitted</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Date of submission of the resource (e.g. thesis, articles, etc.).</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>issued</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Date of formal issuance (e.g., publication) of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>modified</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Date on which the resource was changed.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>valid</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Date (often a range) of validity of a resource.</p>
                  	<!-- same as "File date"?
                  		Most recent date that this object was checked for integrity or at least readability (not necessarily the date the operating system gives). --></dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:W3CDTF</dt>
               	<dd><p>W3C Encoding rules for dates and times - a profile based on ISO
               	   8601 <cit>W3CDTF</cit>.</p></dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
         	<bp>
         	   <p>Minimal best practice is that a record have at least one instance of Date
         		(or one of its refinements).</p>
         	   <p>Minimal best practice is that every instance of Date (or a refinement) use
         	   the <i>dcterms:W3CDTF</i> scheme or a value enclosed in square brackets if
         	   the value does not conform to the encoding scheme.</p>
         		<p>Do not use additional terms (“recorded on”, “donated on”)
         			in the element text <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
         		<p>Do not enter a coded year value and then a mm/dd/yy value in
         			element text. <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
         	</bp>
         	
         	<examples>
               <p>A typical year of publication:</p>
         	   <eg>&lt;dc:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">1992"&lt;/dc:date&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource modified on October 16, 1996:</p>
         	   <eg>&lt;dcterms:modified xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">1996-10-16&lt;/dcterms:modified&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource from approximately 1950:</p>
         		<eg>&lt;dc:date>circa 1950&lt;/dc:date&gt; <!-- what about not using additional terms in the element text? --></eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Description">
         	<definition>An account of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Description may include but is not limited to: an abstract, table of
                  contents, reference to a graphical representation of content, or a
                  free-text account of the content. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>No formatting conventions are defined within the text of Description.
                  Service providers may format the entire Description as a single
                  paragraph, collapsing adjacent white space characters into a single
                  space.</p>
               <p>When there is a URL for a document that describes the resource, use a
                  separate Description element to encode just that URL. A Description that
                  begins with "http:" will be interpreted by service providers as
                  consisting solely of a URL and will be presented as a link in user
                  interfaces. Service providers are not obliged to search other
                  Description text for the occurrence of URLs.</p>
            	<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
            	<p>Description may include but is not limited to: an abstract, table of contents, reference to a graphical representation of content or a free-text account of the content. For the original SIL TOC, use this element to map \anno annotation &lt;annotation&gt;,  a qualitative or evaluative comment about this resource, including judgment about suitability for a particular application or context.</p>
            	<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt --> <!-- under \+mkr descType -->
            	<p>If the description is either an abstract or a table of contents for the resource, that may be specified in this element. If the description is other than one of these, leave \descType empty.</p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 18 -->
            	<p>Clarity and consistency in naming are the most important; there is a specific place in the description that can be used to give additional identifying information.</p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 20 -->
            	<p>The Item level metadata entry carries the information about each specific work. The work can be a stapled paper document, a sound recording on tape, a computer file or several computer files that together constitute a single document. One entry can even contain information about a sub-collection of like items, given that certain qualifications are met. Some types of materials naturally assemble into a sub-collection, such as a group of recordings, texts or photographs in a single language or relating to a single community, etc. Such a collection can be documented in a single metadata entry, provided that:
            		•	All the materials are of the same access level, medium, and type. 
            		•	They are documented in more detail in a separate file included with the collection, which describes each individual piece in terms appropriate to the matieral—see section 2.4.4.
            		•	If submitted on computer media, all materials are grouped into a single parent directory (which may contain subdirectories, as needed).</p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 25-26 -->
            	<p>Documenting a body of materials as a collection, as is typical with a group of recordings or language texts, can be done with simplified documentation in the main TOC file and a supplementary documentation file with details for each text or recording. It should be a text file, preferably tab delimited or tagged, to facilitate loading into a database. Such a file ought to include as much as is known for each text, photograph or recording:
            		•	Label used with original (on tape, box, photo or text), if it uniquely identifies the item within the collection
            		•	Date of work, in yyyymmdd or the appropriate level of precision
            		•	Title, if there is a meaningful title given by the creator
            		•	Title gloss, if useful
            		•	Event or context of recording or photograph
            		•	Keyword description of the genre (e.g., procedure, folk tale, description of event, etc.) or subject
            		•	Length in hh:mm:ss (for recording) or in word count (for a text)
            		•	For recordings or texts
            		o	Speaker or writer’s name, if this is a work of original creation by the speaker (a story teller, an original song, etc.) and thus appropriate to credit the creator (otherwise, maintain the person’s  privacy)
            		o	Speaker age (approximate)
            		o	Speaker gender
            		o	Speaker status or role in community which might be relevant in analyzing a text
            		•	For photographs
            		o	Photographer’s name
            		o	Identifiable subjects’ names (unless this would constitute a violation of privacy as considered in light of the community’s or person’s known preferences), ages, roles in community</p>
            	<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
            	<p>Some types of materials naturally “go together” because they share a lot of identical aspects of their descriptions, for example, a group of texts in recorded or written form narrated or written by the same language informant, or a set of photographs of a single community or event. Think of these groups of related resources as sub-collections. Organizing materials into sub-collections helps a great deal in the descriptive task, because each sub-collection can be documented in a single OLAC metadata entry. Doing this does not mean that the individual items get no individual descriptions. It means that the individual descriptions can be much shorter, more specific, and tailored to the characteristics of the materials. The descriptions of the individual works should be uniform within the sub-collection, but they don’t have to be OLAC-conformant. Only the single “parent” record must be OLAC. The criteria for creating sub-collection descriptions are:
            		•	The sub-collection has a single OLAC record, in which the \type element is repeated and the second instance contains “Collection”. The first instance of \type will reflect the actual type of all the resources: text, still image, or sound, for example. The name of the collection as a whole is given in this record, as are all the metadata contents common to every item in the collection.
            		•	All the materials are of the same access level and are from the same language program. Any other metadata that is common to every item in the collection can also be documented in the OLAC collection record and need not be repeated in the item record. Such things as medium and creator may or may not be the same, but even if they are, it is best to document them in the individual record for the particular text (next point).
            		•	Each item in the sub-collection is documented in a record in a sub-collection description file, which has a set of elements relevant specifically to texts, or to photos, or to whatever kind of thing makes up the sub-collection. These need not be OLAC metadata elements, but if a needed element corresponds to the meaning and usage of a specific OLAC element, use the OLAC element rather than giving it a different label.
            		•	If submitted on computer media, all materials are grouped into a single parent directory (which may contain subdirectories, as needed)
            		Whereas the OLAC metadata record is based on an external standard, the file used to describe a collection can be more flexible, with adjustments particular to the collection itself. Elements used are typically text name, creator(s) and some demographic data about them, other significant participants , date, location, event or setting (“occasion”), literary or musical genre, topic, or any other appropriate specialized information. For texts (including sound recording versions), it is recommended that this be done in a supplementary Toolbox file using the textcat.typ database type definition (the Text_Collection.db is an empty database of this type), which can be kept in the same Toolbox project. Another method may be used, such as a spreadsheet, though keeping track of multiple versions of the same text gets more complicated in a single table or spreadsheet.
            		This sub-collection description file is to be included with the main OLAC metadata file when materials are deposited with an archives. You may wish to create a new database type, possibly based on textcat.typ, for a collection of another kind of resource such as photographs. Where a data elements would be used the same way as an OLAC element, it is best to simply use the same OLAC element (which the textcat.typ does), with the same definitions and appropriate range sets. More ideas about documenting collections can be found in the following article from Notes on Linguistics:
            		Spanne, Joan. 2001. "The linguist’s role in archiving linguistic data resources." Notes on Linguistics 4(1): 4-15.</p>
            	<p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_IMLS.pdf --> The Description element should not be confused with Subject.  Description contains free-text descriptions, while Subject contains subject headings.</p>
            	<p>Description element is not a "catch-all" category.  Consider using Format element for extent or Subject element. <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>abstract</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>A summary of the content of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>tableOfContents</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>A list of subunits of the content of the resource.</p>
                  	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 18 -->
                  	<p>The Table of Contents file can be used to describe materials submitted not only computer media but also in other media, as much of the metadata about the work itself, which does not pertain to the medium of storage, is the same.</p>
                  	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 19 --> <!-- See Table 2 and 3 p. 19-20 and 21-24 -->
                  	<p>A Table of Contents file is the recommended method for submitters to use to describe the materials they are depositing in the archives. It is designed to be human readable (a text format which can be read independent of special software), but also to be usable for automated import into a computer database.... A paper cover sheet can be used to give...descriptive information for materials submitted in paper or other non-computer media.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <bp>
               <p>Minimal best practice is that a metadata record should contain at least
               one Description or Subject element.</p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 18-->
            	<p>For computer files, great levels of detail in the file organization and complex coded naming schemes for file names are generally less satisfactory than explicit descriptions of the files included on a given media unit. Coded file naming schemes are difficult to apply accurately and can lead to mistakes in description and potentially to loss of materials actually in the collection, because they cannot be identified. For this reason, it is best to explicitly describe files (and dependently related sets of files) in a document such as a Table Of Contents file.</p>
         	</bp>
         	
            <examples>
               <p>A prose description of a resource:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:description&gt;The CALLHOME Japanese corpus of telephone
   speech consists of 120 unscripted telephone conversations between native
   speakers of Japanese. All calls, which lasted up to 30 minutes,
   originated in North America and were placed to locations overseas
   (typically Japan). Most participants called family members or close
   friends. This corpus contains speech data files ONLY, along with the
   minimal amount of documentation needed to describe the contents and
   format of the speech files and the software packages needed to
   uncompress the speech data. &lt;/dc:description&gt;</eg>
               <p>A reference to an existing on-line description:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:description&gt;http://www.ldc.upenn.edu/Catalog/LDC96S37.html<br/>&lt;/dc:description&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Format">
         	<definition>The file format, physical medium, or dimensions of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Typically, Format may include the media-type or dimensions of the
                  resource. Format may be used to determine the software, hardware or
                  other equipment needed to display or operate the resource. Examples of
                  dimensions include size and duration. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>The element content may be left empty, but it would typically be
                  used to add further details about the format of the resource, such
                  as the sampling rate for digital recordings, the size of computer
                  files, the number of pages and dimensions of a book, the
                  appearance of a physical object, and so on. </p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 14 --> <!-- Refer to and adapt Table 1 p. 14-15? -->
            	<p>The procedures, media and formats for unpublished materials are very much dependent upon the nature of materials and the anticipated uses, both short- and long-term. Table 1 gives suggestions for what should be submitted by users, but it only addresses common types of materials. If possible, both a source and a presentation form of the work should be submitted. </p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 47-48 -->
            	<p>The FORMAT of a computer file refers to the encoding scheme used to represent the data (in 1’s and 0’s), and relates to the software and/or hardware required to access and use the object. Usually represented by the suffix of a computer file name, e.g., WAV or MP3 for sound recording objects, TIFF, JPEG, GIF, BMP for images, MPEG for full-motion image streams, DOC for a Word document, XML for an eXtensible Markup Language document, SFM for a Standard Format Marked data file.</p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 35 -->
            	<p>Web content of a more document-like nature (a specific title, a credited author, and a date), such as an electronic working paper series, should be archived, and can usually be handled similarly to a print publication. Articles written by SIL authors for electronic journals or other formal web publications on other web sites should also be archived. Materials initially published in print (or on audio cassette, etc.) and converted for the web should be elsewhere included in the archives collection, though the new computer form (PDF, HTML, MP3) might also be suitable for maintaining as a presentation form.</p>
            	<p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_IMLS.pdf -->Format, which includes the names of media types such as photograph, should not be confused with Type, which categorizes the nature or genre of the content of the resource and includes terms that describe general categories, functions, genres, or aggregation levels for content.</p>
            	<p>Need to differentiate IMT (Internet Media Type code) from a Type code. <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
            		<p>Also for medium and extent information (however, no
            			instance for either DC qualifier was actually specified) <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --> </p>
            		<p>OLAC had 5 refinements (cpu, encoding, markup, os,
            			sourcecode) but each of these was used very little, if at all <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>extent</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The size or duration of the resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>medium</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The material or physical carrier of the resource.</p>
                  	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 48 -->
                  	<p>Physical manifestation of an information object or information storage unit,  e.g., paper, acid-free paper, microfilm, microfiche, 35 mm slide, 16 mm film, audio cassette, reel-to-reel sound recording, video cassette, CD-R, Mini-disc, DVD, Digital Audio Tape (DAT) or computer hard disk. Sometimes used synonymously with “format” in its physical sense, but that use of “format” has been avoided in this document.</p>
                  	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 13-14 -->
                  	<p>Published materials which are produced in paper or other non-computer media should be archived in that medium.... However, data sets and language texts (including Scripture portions) are resource types that are almost always sought in source form for use in further linguistic analysis or for later revision, no matter the age of the data or text. For such materials, the need is for long term preservation of a computer based source form. A non-proprietary, standardized format, such as SFM or XML, is most desirable. </p>
                  	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 48 -->
                  	<p>e.g., paper, acid-free paper, microfilm, microfiche, 35 mm slide, 16 mm film, audio cassette, reel-to-reel sound recording, video cassette, CD-R, Mini-disc, DVD, Digital Audio Tape (DAT) or computer hard disk. Sometimes used synonymously with “format” in its physical sense, but that use of “format” has been avoided in this document.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>

            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:IMT</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The Internet media type of the resource.<cit>IMT</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
            	<p>In the case of a digital resource, recommended best practice is to express
            	   the format using a MIME type from the <i>dcterms:IMT</i> scheme. </p>
            </bp>
            <examples>
               <p>For a digitally encoded dictionary:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT">text/xml&lt;/dc:format>
               	&lt;dcterms:extent&gt;5,237 entries in a 1.2M XML file.&lt;/dcterms:extent&gt;</eg>
               <p>For a digitally recorded text:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT">audio/wav&lt;/dc:format>
&lt;dc:format>Sampling: 1 channel, 22 KHz, 8 bits.&lt;/dc:format>
&lt;dcterms:extent>Duration: 153 seconds. Size: 3.3M. &lt;/dcterms:extent></eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
      	<!-- Identifier would probably benefit from a
      		more thorough best practice document.  --><!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf -->
         <element name="Identifier">
            <definition>An unambiguous reference to the resource within a given context.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>In the case of a resource that is not electronically encoded, but is
                  housed in a conventional archive, Identifier may be used to give a local
                  shelf or box number, or whatever scheme is used to locate a resource
                  within the collection.</p>
               <p>Identifiers that begin with "http:" will be interpreted by service
                  providers as URLs and be presented as links in user interfaces. Note
                  that Identifier is to be used only for a URL that retrieves the actual
                  resource; use <xref>Description</xref> for a URL that retrieves just a
                  description of the resource.</p>
               <p>Do not specify the "oai:" identifier for the resource itself as a value
                  of Identifier, since it is already given in
                     <tt>&lt;identifier&gt;</tt> in the
                  <tt>&lt;header&gt;</tt> of the <tt>&lt;record&gt;</tt>s
                  returned by the OAI protocol.</p>
            	<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
               <p>Filename (including path if on a CD-R or DVD that is being deposited) of file folder of set of files if this is a digital resource. URL for work published online. ISBN for hard-copy publication, if available, or bibliographic citation if not. (Place, publisher, [series and volume] for a monograph; journal title, vol., issue and pages for an article; editor, place, publisher, [series and volume] and pages for book-chapter; name, location and date of conference for a conference paper; degree level and institution for a thesis.)</p>
            	<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
            	<p>The expectation is that all the materials originating from a specific language program will constitute one collection. Where two (or more) separate programs have operated in a single language (using the list of ISO 639-3  identified languages as reference), the Specific Collection Identifier can also include some distinguishing information, such as dialect.
            		For example, a project in the Leemo dialect of the Hadiyya language of Ethiopia would construct a primary identifier as:
            		ETG-hdy_Leemo-001.</p>
            		<p>Alternatively, it might be desirable to gather materials from a single program that serves multiple languages into a single set of records. To indicate a cluster language program, use the same name (or a code) used within the entity to identify the program. The language of any one resource is specified within its particular metadata record. Codes of three letters for other than ISO language codes should be avoided in the Specific Collection Identifier segment (but other code schemas may be okay).</p>
            	      <p>For materials that originate from other than language program work, a different identification is needed. This could be an author’s surname for the collection of works by one scholar. It could also be a department name for materials pertaining to a specific department, e.g., SurveyDept.</p>
            	<p>– Many non-unique Identifier URLs:
            		• In a few archives, multiple resources were
            		‘identified’ with the same URL, usually availability
            		info or a further description, but not the resource
            		itself
            		• Often apparently mistaken as the only place one
            		could put a URL associated with this resource
            		• Sometimes incomplete (relative?) paths given
            		– Some identifiers seemed useful only to the archives, but
            		were not relevant for resource discovery or request for
            		access <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>bibliographicCitation</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>A bibliographic reference for the resource.
                  		Comment:  Recommended practice is to include sufficient bibliographic detail to identify the resource as unambiguously as possible, whether or not the citation is in a standard form. 
                  	</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
               	<dd><p>A URI Uniform Resource Identifier.<cit>URI</cit>.</p></dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
         	<bp>
         		<p>Recommended best practice is to specify the <i>dcterms;URI</i> scheme when
         		   the value is a Uniform Resource Locator (URL).</p>
         	</bp>
         	
            <examples>
               <p>A Uniform Resource Locator for retrieval of an electronically encoded
                  resource:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:identifier xsi:type="dcterms:URI"&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/cs.CL/0010033&lt;/dc:identifier&gt;</eg>
               <p>A local identifier for retrieval within a physical collection:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:identifier&gt;Shelf 12, Box 7&lt;/dc:identifier&gt;</eg>
               <p>The citation for a chapter that was published in a book:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dcterms:bibliographicCitation&gt;In Joel Sherzer and Greg
                  Urban (eds.), Native South American discourse, 237-306. Berlin: Mouton.
                  &lt;dcterms:bibliographicCitation&gt;</eg>
               
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Language">
         	<definition>A language of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Language is used for a language the resource is in, as opposed to the
                  language it describes (see <xref>Subject.language</xref>). It is related
                  to the audience for the work in that it identifies a language that the
                  creator of the resource assumes that its eventual user will understand.
                  When a resource is in more than one language, use a separate Language
                  element for each language.</p>
               <p>For a work of literature or other monolingual document aimed at the
                  speakers of a particular language, use Language to identify that
                  language. For a sound recording, use Language for the language being
                  spoken in the recording. For a grammatical description, for instance,
                  use Language for the language the grammar is written in; use
                  Subject.language for the language whose grammar is being described. For
                  an annotated text, use Language for the language in which the
                  annotations are made; use Subject.language for the language of the base
                  text that is being annotated. For a dictionary, use Language for the
                  language in which the definitions are written; use Subject.language for
                  the language whose words are being defined.</p>
            	<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
            	<p>For scholarly works, this will usually be a major language (English, French, Indonesian, etc.). For vernacular works, it will be the minority language and will usually be the same as the language coded in subject_language. Repeat tag for each code needed for polyglot works. Give the language name in this element, if it is a specific variety of the language as identified using its three-letter ISO 6390-3 identifier, which should be given in \language_code.</p>            	
               <!-- Following from Joan Spanne's SIL_Guidelines. -->
               <p>PLEASE make an effort to use and keep up to date the Ethnologue code identification of collections, rather than using an entity developed code for individual languages, as entity specific codes become confusing or misleading when removed from the immediate entity context.</p>
            	<p>May need to clarify between language name or code and attribute supplying
            		OLAC language code. <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>olac:ISO639-3</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The ISO 639-3 set of three-letter identifiers for the
                        identification of human languages. See
                           <cit>OLAC-Language</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. </p>                  	
                  	<!-- Move to a <bp><p>? -->
                     <p>Recommended best practice is to specify the language via the
                           <i>code</i> attribute while leaving the element content empty.
                        Use the element content only when the controlled vocabulary does
                        not offer an appropriate code, or when further specification is
                        needed, such as to name a specific dialect or to give an alternate
                        name that differs from the default name given by the controlled
                        vocabulary. </p>
                     <p>Service providers should use the <i>code</i> attribute to support
                        searches by language, and may use the element content in searches
                        by keyword. They also may supply the default language name in
                        keyword searching when the element content is missing.</p>
                  	<!-- What about md-lang from OLACSIL.txt ? -->  <!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
                  	<p> \desc The language in which this metadata record is primarily written (not including coded range-set values). Multiple titles (using alternative), descriptions, and subject terms may be given in additional languages to aid in searching; specify the language used for each of those if different from the language specified in this element. </p>                 	
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
            	<p>Minimal best practice is that every record contain at least one Language
            	element.</p>
               <p>Minimal best practice is that every Language
                  element use the <i>olac:ISO639-3</i> scheme to identify it precisely.</p>
            	<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
              <p>[For more than one language repeat the] \language and \subject_language [elements], which have sub-elements for ISO code language identifiers.</p>
            </bp>
         	
         	<examples>
               <p>A resource in English about the Sikaiana language:</p>
         		<eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="eng"/&gt;
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="sky"/&gt;</eg>
               <p>A Yemba-French dictionary, where the alternate name Dschang is
                  preferred.</p>
         	   <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="fra"/&gt;
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="ybb"&gt;Dschang&lt;/dc:language&gt;</eg>
               <p>The <i>American Heritage Dictionary</i>, which is both in and about
                  American English:</p>
         	   <eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="eng"/&gt; 
&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="eng"/&gt; 
&lt;dcterms:spatial&gt;United States&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
               <p>A resource about a language for which the controlled vocabulary does not
                  yet provide a code:</p>
         		<eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language"&gt;Ancient Sumerian&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
            <todo>
               <p>Add an example of specifying a dialect.</p>
               <p>Do we want olac:ISO639-3 (analogous to dcterms:ISO639-2) or
                  olac:language so that we can use it without a code?</p>
               <p>Write the OLAC-Language document.</p>
            </todo>
         </element>
         <element name="Provenance">
         	<!-- Provenance is not in "Section 2: The Dublin Core Metadata Element Set" at http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/.  It is found in "Section 3: Other Elements and Element Refinements" -->
         	<definition>A statement of any changes in ownership and custody of the resource since its creation that are significant for its authenticity, integrity and interpretation.</definition>
            <comment>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 48 -->
            	<p>PROVENANCE: 1) The individual, department or agency that created, accumulated, maintained and/or used materials (data sources, documents). 2) Information regarding the origin and custodial history of documents or data sources. The Principle of Provenance (also known as “respect des fonds”), a foundational principle of archives management, is that materials of the same provenance must not be intermingled with those of any other provenance. It is the principle of provenance that is the basis for arranging and storing materials by language project (as the original setting of creation and accumulation), rather than extracting and collocating all grammar materials, all anthropology materials, all instances of a shell book, etc. into topical collections in the archives.</p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 17-->
            	<p>Unlike a library, which usually organizes works by topic, the archive should organize materials by common origin or provenance.... In general, it is best to keep collections together as a physical unit (as much as the different types of media permit), with each language program collection stored on its own computer media unit (such as CD-R), or all together in adjacent paper files. This most easily enables a particular team to see what has been submitted in the past and maintains the physical integrity of each collection consistently for archives management procedures.... the archives should not mix materials from different collections...according to...topical categories.</p>
            </comment>
         </element>
         <element name="Publisher">
         	<definition>An entity responsible for making the resource available.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Examples of a Publisher include a person, an organization, or a service.
                  Typically, the name of a Publisher should be used to indicate the
                  entity. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 35 -->
            	<p>Content (documents, web pages—text, graphics, streaming audio and video) created for and published on the World Wide Web on a sanctioned entity site comprises a special class of published materials. Web content of a more document-like nature (a specific title, a credited author, and a date), such as an electronic working paper series, should be archived, and can usually be handled similarly to a print publication. Articles written by SIL authors for electronic journals or other formal web publications on other web sites should also be archived. Materials initially published in print (or on audio cassette, etc.) and converted for the web should be elsewhere included in the archives collection, though the new computer form (PDF, HTML, MP3) might also be suitable for maintaining as a presentation form.</p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 35 on advisability of including UNPUBLISHED materials -->
            	<p>Caring for unpublished resources of long term value ... Language data, either in lexical form (a database) or as a text (with documentation) is more and more sought after as input for computational linguistic analysis. Descriptions and analyses are also desirable, if they are of reasonably good quality (e.g. consultant checked). Translation by-products, such as key terms papers and back translations, can be very useful to other teams in related languages. Language surveys and their supporting data are very valuable. Collected texts, recorded language data and transcriptions, if of sufficiently good quality, are also very valuable, as are photographs and slides, but the complexities resulting from lack of context (if not well documented) and ethical considerations add to the challenges of managing them in the archives .</p>
            	<p>Being selective about what should be archived is important. Selectivity imposes an extra initial labor cost, but one which pays dividends in the short and long runs. For the submitter, being selective reduces the amount of material submitted, and therefore, reduces the burden of describing the material as well. For the archives, every object has a cost of storage, migration and management, which is balanced against its short and long term value. Is this a work that will be useful or informative in the future?  Is it unique?  Is it something that can no longer be obtained elsewhere?  Is it reasonably good quality?  ‘Yes’ to these indicates that a work is probably worth keeping.</p>
            	<p>Usually a publisher or the archives itself,
            		sometimes with URL, sometimes URL
            		given in separate instance of element. Do not use it for host publication
            		information, which should be in Relation.<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
            </comment>
         	<bp>
         		<p>Recommended best practice is to identify a Publisher by means of a name
         			in a form that is ready for sorting within an
         			index. For the names of persons, this means that the name should be
         			given in inverted order with the surname first. For the names of
         			organizations, this means that any initial article should be omitted.</p>
         		<p>Copyright statement should be in text of element, not in
         			the ‘code’ <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
         		<p>Rights developments:
         			– With the Access extension on Rights, OLAC is
         			integrating access and permitted use
         			– Leave the work to the content of the element or a
         			referral to additional information</p>
         			<p>Additional good practice guidance is needed
         			regarding parameters of protection: duration of
         			restriction, entity with authority to override,
         			expectations placed on users <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
         		<p>– Identifier was used (repeated) for what clearly had to be
         			a Source resource URL (based on contextual content of
         			record)
         			– Source was used to give information on the linguistic
         			consultant, with lengthy description. The whole would
         			have been more appropriate in Description element.
         			(Contributor was used also)
         			– Source was used to specify an entity responsible for
         			development, creation, donation, etc. of the resource (in
         			one a Ph.D. granting institution is named, another the
         			gov. agency responsible, others, SIL is named) <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf -->
         		</p>
         	</bp>
         	
         	<examples>
               <p>A typical publisher:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:publisher&gt;Oxford University Press&lt;/dc:publisher&gt;</eg>
               <p>The URL for a publisher:</p>
         	   <eg>&lt;dc:publisher xsi:type="dcterms:URI"&gt;http://www.oup.com&lt;/dc:publisher&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Relation">
         	<definition>A related resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>This element is used to document relationships between resources, for
                  instance, part-whole relationships, version relationships, dependency
                  relationships, and so on. When the related resource is also in a
                  participating archive, the reference to the related resource should be
                  by means of an "oai:" identifier. A Relation that begins with "oai:"
                  should be presented by service providers as an active link that
                  retrieves the metadata for that resource.</p>
               <p>For a required markup definition (like a DTD or Schema) use
                     <xref>Format.markup</xref> rather than Relation. When the required
                  software or hardware can be inferred from the <xref>Format</xref> of the
                  resource, do not also use Relation for this purpose.</p>
               <p>When the present resource is a derived work, the source resource is
                  typically indicated by <xref>Source</xref>. However, there are two cases
                  in which refinements of Relation are used for derived works. The
                     <i>isVersionOf</i> refinement is used when the present resource is a
                  new version or edition with added intellectual content that has been
                  developed by the same creators. When the new version is nothing more
                  than a rendition in a new format, then the <i>isForrmatOf</i> refinement
                  is used. </p>
            	<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
            	<p>Use this element to associate independent but conceptually related materials. Use the \relationType element to specify the nature of the relationship between the work described in this record and the work whose ID is given in this element.  Repeat for each related item.  Use an unambiguous identifier (such as the \primaryid) for the related resource, if possible, or a standard name for a schema to which this resource conforms, e.g., GOLD: General Ontology for Linguistic Description.</p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 16 -->
            	<p>Relationship metadata pertains to relationships among independent objects, such as print/analog and digital forms of the same content, presentation and source forms, a dissertation and a book which came directly from it. This must not be confused with the administrative metadata elements that link distinct but dependent parts of a larger whole.</p>
            	<p>“Previously” could utilize “Replaces” <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>conformsTo</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>A reference to an established standard to which the resource conforms.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>hasFormat</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource pre-existed the referenced resource, which is essentially the same intellectual content presented in another format.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>hasPart</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource includes the referenced resource either physically or logically.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>hasVersion</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource has a version, edition, or adaptation, namely, the referenced resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>isFormatOf</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource is the same intellectual content of the referenced resource, but presented in another format.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>isPartOf</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource is a physical or logical part of the referenced resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>isReferencedBy</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource is referenced, cited, or otherwise pointed to by the referenced resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>isReplacedBy</dt>
                  <dd/>
                  <dt>isRequiredBy</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource is required by the referenced resource, either physically or logically.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>isVersionOf</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource is a version, edition, or adaptation of the referenced resource. Changes in version imply substantive changes in content rather than differences in format.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>references</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource references, cites, or otherwise points to the referenced resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>replaces</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource supplants, displaces, or supersedes the referenced resource.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>requires</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>The described resource requires the referenced resource to support its function, delivery, or coherence of content.</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
               	<dd><p>A URI Uniform Resource Identifier.<cit>URI</cit>.</p></dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
            	<p>When the related resource is also held in a participating archive,
            	   recommended best practice is to identify the related resource by means of
            	   its OAI identifier. </p>
            	<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
            	<p>In general, element properties—the labels, definitions, and range sets, should not be changed. However, two of the properties that may be changed are the font used for a specific field, and the language properties assigned to the field. This is the way that a field can be made to use a different (Unicode compliant) font and specific rules for word breaks, etc. that differ from those applied to other fields.A good candidate for customizing this way is the \title field, or the \alternative field. Keep in mind that all instances of that field will use the same font. The font should be a Unicode compliant font, not a legacy font that substitutes some characters with other characters (characters with different meanings, not just different representations). A custom font that has been developed to render Unicode characters better than or not available in generic Unicode fonts like Arial Unicode MS or Doulos SIL may be used. Be sure to document the font itself as a resource, and include it among the computer files of your collection. If these are foreign concepts, then don’t worry about this.</p>
            </bp>
         	
         	<examples>
               <p>A link to a required font:</p>
         		<eg>&lt;dcterms:requires&gt;oai:sil:software/ipafont&lt;/dcterms:requires&gt;</eg>
               <p>Links to the component pieces of a collected work:</p>
         		<eg>&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding126&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding127&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding128&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding129&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding130&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;</eg>
         	</examples>
            <todo><p>Do we need a scheme for olac:OAI to represent an OLAC OAI identifier?
            Or should we just use dcterms:URI and match on initial "oai:"?</p></todo>
         </element>
         <element name="Rights">
         	<definition>Information about rights held in and over the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p> Typically, a Rights element will contain a rights management statement
                  for the resource, or reference a service providing such information.
                  Rights information often encompasses Intellectual Property Rights (IPR),
                  Copyright, and various Property Rights. If the Rights element is absent,
                  no assumptions can be made about the status of these and other rights
                  with respect to the resource. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 12 -->
            	<p>Copyrights are also inherent in primary linguistic and cultural research materials, such as stories, descriptions, songs or art work, which researcher collect in the course of their work. The rights, in most cases, belong to the creator—not the researcher or SIL—or, in some cases, to the language community (as a legal entity). Intellectual property law as it applies to community cultural property is not yet well-defined and is beyond the scope of these guidelines. However, documenting the creators of such works and the conditions under which they came into the hands of an SIL worker are critical steps in archiving these valuable works. Only with this information about their origins can SIL follow through on its intention to respect the intellectual property rights of vernacular language communities in which we work.</p>
            	<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
            	<p>Specify a license, access conditions (for the public) or rights holders specific to this item. A rights holder may be the publisher, if the author assigned rights to the work in a publication contract, or a member of a language community if the work is that person’s creative initiative and he/she was not in the employ of an entity language project. (Do not include SIL International, an SIL entity or a WO, as the appropriate authority is assumed based on the primary id.) If the Rights element is absent, no assumptions can be made about the status of these and other rights with respect to the resource.</p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p.26-->
            	<p>Texts and recordings are collected by a language worker often based on an assumption of private use for research. However, they are the intellectual property of someone else. The original writer or speaker, or perhaps the language community as a body, might want to assert ownership if texts or recordings are used for a purpose besides the original collector’s private study. To publish or otherwise distribute these works should have the approval of the owner—the creator. Because of this, special documentation is needed in an archives context. For language texts it is wise to document the speaker’s name, basic demographic information , the context in which collecting took place, and the date.</p>
            	<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p.26-->
            	<p>Photographs, similarly, are usually taken in a context assuming private use, unless a media person explicitly states other intentions. Though the photograph is the intellectual property of the photographer, publication of a photograph with identifiable persons should take into consideration their privacy rights and preferences.</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>accessRights</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Information about who can access the resource or an indication of its security status.
                  		Comment:  Access Rights may include information regarding access or restrictions based on privacy, security or other regulations. 
                  	</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>license</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>A legal document giving official permission to do something with the resource.
                  		Comment:  Recommended best practice is to identify the license using a URI. Examples of such licenses can be found at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/. 
                  	</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
         	
         	<todo>
               <p>Mention Creative Commons in the usage notes and give an example of a CC
                  license statement.</p>
            </todo>
         </element>
         <element name="Rights Holder">
         	<!-- Rights Holder is not in this order in the DCMI listing at http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/.  It is found in "Section 3: Other Elements and Element Refinements" (in alphabetical order). -->
         	<definition>A person or organization owning or managing rights over the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Use the URI or name of the Rights Holder to indicate the entity.</p>
            </comment>
         	
         </element>
         <element name="Source">
         	<definition>The resource from which the described resource is derived.</definition>
            <comment>
             <!-- Move to <bp><p>? -->  
            	<p>The present resource may be derived from the Source resource in whole or
                  in part. <cit>DCMT</cit> When the Source resource is also available in
                  an on-line archive, recommended best practice is to reference it by
                  means of an "oai:" identifier. In this case service providers should
                  presented the Source as an active link that retrieves the metadata for
                  that resource. </p>
               <p> In the legal parlance of intellectual property rights, a "derivative
                  work" is one that is based on one or more preexisting works. This
                  includes cases in which a work may be recast, transformed, or adapted in
                  any way, such as by translation, abridgement, dramatization, recording,
                  transcription, or digital encoding. A work consisting of editorial
                  revisions, annotations, elaborations, or other modifications, which, as
                  a whole, represent an original work of authorship is also a derivative
                  work <cit>Copyright</cit>.</p>
               <p>This legal definition elucidates the sense of "derived" that is intended
                  in the Dublin Core definition of Source. Note, however, that this
                  overlaps with <xref>Relation</xref>, since the <i>isFormatOf</i> and
                     <i>isVersionOf</i> refinements both refer to derivative works in the
                  technical sense.</p>
               <p>Use Source (as opposed to Relation) in 
                  cases when the present resource has a substantially different
                  <xref>Type</xref> or <xref>Creator</xref> or <xref>Title</xref> than the
                  Source resource. When the difference from the original work is only a
                  difference of <xref>Date</xref> or <xref>Format</xref> or
                  <xref>Publisher</xref> or <xref>Identifier</xref> or edition
                  designator in the <xref>Title</xref>, then use Relation to encode the
                  relationship to the original work.</p>
               
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
               	<dd><p>A URI Uniform Resource Identifier.<cit>URI</cit>.</p> 
               	</dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>When the Source resource is also held in a participating archive,
                  recommended best practice is to identify the related resource by means of
                  its OAI identifier. </p>
            </bp>
         	
         	<examples>
               <p>Source for a digital encoding of a manuscript in a participating
                  archive:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:source&gt;oai:somearchive:holding1023&lt;/dc:source&gt;</eg>
               <p>Source for data extracted from a published source:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:source&gt;Kwara'ae flora vocabulary extracted from Guide to
the Forests of the British Solomon Islands, by T. C. Whitmore. Oxford
University Press, 1966.&lt;/dc:source&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
         <element name="Subject">
         	<definition>The topic of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Typically, a Subject will be expressed as keywords, key phrases or
                  classification codes that describe a topic of the resource.
                  <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>To describe the spatial or temporal topic of the resource, use the <xref>Coverage</xref> element.</p>
               <p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_IMLS.pdf --> The Subject element should not be confused with Description.  Subject contains subject headings, while Description contains free-text descriptions.</p>
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>olac:ISO639-3</dt>
                  <dd>
                     <p>The ISO 639-3 set of three-letter identifiers for the
                        identification of human languages. See <xref>Language</xref> for a complete discussion (with examples) of
                        using this scheme.</p>
                     <!-- Move to a <bp><p>? -->
                     <p>Recommended best practice is to specify the language via the
                        <i>code</i> attribute while leaving the element content empty.
                        Use the element content only when the controlled vocabulary does
                        not offer an appropriate code, or when further specification is
                        needed, such as to name a specific dialect or to give an alternate
                        name that differs from the default name given by the controlled
                        vocabulary. </p>
                     <p>Service providers should use the <i>code</i> attribute to support
                        searches by language, and may use the element content in searches
                        by keyword. They also may supply the default language name in
                        keyword searching when the element content is missing.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>olac:linguistic-field</dt>
                  <dd><p>The OLAC vocabulary for describing the content of a resource as
                     relevant to a particular subfield of linguistic science
                     <cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Field</cit>. </p></dd>
               </dl>
           </schemes>    
            <bp>
               <p>Minimal best practice is that a metadata record should contain at least
                  one Description or Subject element.</p>
            	<p>When the subject is a human language, minimal best practice is to use
            	   the <i>olac:ISO639-3</i> scheme to identify it precisely.</p>
               <p>When the subject matter falls within the field of linguistics, recommended best practice is to use
                  the <i>olac:linguistic-field</i> scheme to identify the subfield.</p>           	
            	<p><!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->Recommended best practice is to select a value from a controlled vocabulary or formal classification scheme, such as: DDC, or LCSH. Use to indicate topic or type of resource if not identified in other elements, e.g., Health book, Optimized phonological description, Language survey; Anthropology field notes; also use topical words such as Tone; Verb structure; Kinship.</p>
            	<p>Element should be repeated for multiple subject
            		terms <!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
            </bp>
         	
         	<examples>
               <p>A Library of Congress subject heading:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="dcterms:LCSH"&gt;African languages&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
            <todo>
               <p>Geographic and temporal aspects of language varieties go in Coverage.
                  Subject is where social dimensions of language varieties would go. Add an
                  example.</p>
            </todo>
         </element>
         <element name="Title">
         	<definition>A name given to the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p>Typically, a Title will be a name by which the resource is formally
                  known. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
               <p>A translation of the title can be supplied in a second Title element.
                  Use the <i>lang</i> attribute to identify the language of these
                  elements.</p>
            	<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
            	<p>[Can be] a name given to a work to identify it if a formal title is not used, such as for a data set or collection of texts. For a formal title, this is generally in the language in which the work is written or recorded. If the title is in a language different from the language identified in \md-lang, note the language of the title in the \titleLang field.</p>
            </comment>
            <refinements>
               <dl>
                  <dt>alternative</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>Any form of the title used as a substitute or alternative to the formal title of the resource.
                  		Comment:  This qualifier can include Title abbreviations as well as translations. 
                  	</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </refinements>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt/>
               	<!-- Empty definition term. -->
               	<dd>
                    <!-- Move to <bp><p>? --> 
                  	<p>The <i>refine</i> attribute may optionally be used for a single
                        refinement supported by <cit>DC-Q</cit>. The value
                        <i>alternative</i> indicates a form of the title that is used as a
                        substitute or alternative to the formal title of the resource.
                        This qualifier can include abbreviated titles as well as
                        translations. </p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Minimal best practice is that every record must have an instance of the
                  Title element.</p>
               <p>Recommended best practice is that only one instance
                  of Title, namely the original title, be unqualified.
                  All others (e.g. translations)
                  should be specified as the Alternative refinement.</p>
            </bp>
         	
            <examples>
               <p>A typical title:</p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;A Dictionary of the Nggela Language&lt;/dc:title&gt;</eg>
               <p>A vernacular title with translation:</p>
            	<eg>&lt;dc:title xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="llu"&gt;Na tala 'uria na idulaa diana&lt;/dc:title&gt;
            	   &lt;dcterms:alternative xml:lang="eng" &gt;The road to good reading&lt;/dcterms:alternative&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
         </element>
      	<!-- Type:   i Exhibited perhaps the most different archivespecific
      		interpretations of its use
      		i Evidence of different vocabularies for type used
      		by numerous archives
      		i When coded, the codes were generally applied
      		correctly
      		i Abused by some poor mappings -->
      	<!-- iMore thorough best practice guidelines for:
      		– Description
      		– Identifier
      		– Rights
      		– Subject qualifiers and extensions (dealing with
      		overlap, use of multiple schemes)
      		– Type and its extensions
      		iThe definitions and controlled vocabularies
      		have to be in order FIRST -->
      	<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf -->
         <element name="Type">
         	<definition>The nature or genre of the resource.</definition>
            <comment>
               <p> Type includes terms describing general categories, functions, genres,
                  or aggregation levels for content. To describe the physical or digital
                  manifestation of the resource, use the <xref>Format</xref> element.
                     <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
            	<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
            	<p>Select from the closed range of resource types; some have subtypes further specified. This relates to the intended use or mode of perception by a user, e.g., a computer image file of a text (such as a scanned document) is type 'text', not type 'image'. The list here contains all the DCMI:Type vocabulary terms and the terms of HIS: RMR_mode where those differ from DCMI:Type</p>
            </comment>
            <schemes>
               <dl>
                  <dt>dcterms:DCMIType</dt>
                  <dd>
                  	<p>A list of types used to categorize the nature or genre of the content of the resource.
                  		<cit>DCMI-Type</cit>.</p>
                  </dd>
                  <dt>olac:linguistic-type</dt>
                  <dd><p>The nature or genre of the content of the resource from a
                     linguistic standpoint <cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Type</cit>. For a resource that is information in or about a language,
                     use this scheme to identify what kind of information it is from a
                     linguistic standpoint.</p>
                  <!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
                  <p>Linguistic Type extension of the Type element should only be used if a resource represents one of the structural types in the range set. The element may be repeated if a resource represents more than one linguistic type. So, for example, a primary text accompanied by a lexicon of vocabulary items would be described as both a primary text and a lexicon. 
                  	In many cases, adequate description of a linguistic resource will require that the Linguistic Type extension be used in conjunction with the Discourse Type extension of the Type element, or the Linguistic extension of the Subject element. For example, a narrative text might be described as both a primary text (OLAC Linguistic Type) and a narrative (OLAC Discourse Type).</p>
                  </dd>
               </dl>
            </schemes>
            <bp>
               <p>Minimal best practice is that every record contain at least one Type
                  element that uses the <i>dcterms:DCMIType</i> scheme.</p>
               <p>When a resource is an instance of  language data, documentation, or
                  description, minimal best practice is to use the
                  <i>olac:linguistic-type</i> scheme to identify its linguistic data type. </p>
           </bp>

            <examples>
               <p>The resource is a video recording:<!-- Is "video recording" really a Type and not Format (because 'photograph' was an example of Format according to Jung-ran Park.)? Need examples to contrast Format and Type. --></p>
               <eg>&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage&lt;/cd:type&gt;</eg>
            </examples>
            <todo><p>The following is leftover from 2002; do we still want it?  For a resource that is a software tool,
               Type.linguistic identifies what kind of information it processes.
               Service providers may use this information to match data files with
               software tools that might be applied to them.</p></todo>
         </element>
      </section>
   </body>
   <todo>
      <p>There is not yet a provision for handling subject categorization by linguistic
         (genetic) classification.</p>
      <p>Rights.software has been left in limbo. It may be possible to unify it with
         Rights.</p>
   </todo>
   <references>
      <ref abbrev="Copyright">Section 101, Definitions, Copyright Law of the United States
         of America and Related Laws Contained in Title 17 of the United States
            Code.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.loc.gov/copyright/title17/92chap1.html#101</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMT">Dublin Core Metadata Terms.
         <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/</url>&gt;</ref>
   	
      <ref abbrev="DC-Q">Dublin Core
            Qualifiers.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/07/11/DCMT-qualifiers/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCQ-HTML">Recording qualified Dublin Core metadata in HTML meta
            elements.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/08/15/dcq-html/</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMI-Registry">DCMI Open Metadata
            Registry.<br/>&lt;<url>http://wip.dublincore.org:8080/registry/Registry</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="DCMI-Submit">DCMI Open Metadata Registry: Submit a Scheme for
            Registration.<br/>&lt;<url>http://wip.dublincore.org:8080/registry/authServlet?req_type=newscheme&amp;lang=enUS</url>&gt;</ref>

   	<ref abbrev="DCMI-Box">DCMI Box
   		<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/07/11/dcmi-type-vocabulary/</url>&gt;</ref>

   	<ref abbrev="DCMI-Point">DCMI Point
   		<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-point/</url>&gt;</ref>
   	
   	<ref abbrev="DCMI-Type">DCMI Type Vocabulary.
   	   <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-type-vocabulary/</url>&gt;</ref>
   	
      <ref abbrev="IANA-CS">Internet Character Sets.<br/>
         &lt;<url>http://www.isi.edu/in-notes/iana/assignments/character-sets</url>&gt;</ref>
      
      <ref abbrev="IMT">IMT
   		<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/</url>&gt;</ref>
   	
      <ref abbrev="ISO639-3">ISO 639: Codes for the representation of names of languages - Part 3: Alpha-3 code for comprehensive coverage of languages.<br/>
         &lt;<url>http://www.sil.org/iso639-3/</url>&gt;</ref>
      
      <ref abbrev="URI">URI
   		<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2396.txt</url>&gt;</ref>
   	
      <ref abbrev="MIME">Internet Media
            Types.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.isi.edu/in-notes/iana/assignments/media-types/media-types</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OAI">Open Archives Initiative.
            <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/</url>&gt;</ref>
      
      <ref abbrev="OLAC-BP">Best Practice Recommendations for Language Resource
         Description.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/bpr.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Linguistic-Field">OLAC Linguistic Subject
         Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/field.htmll</url>&gt;</ref>
      
      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Linguistic-Type">OLAC Linguistic Data Type
         Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/type.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Metadata">OLAC
            Metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Language">OLAC Language
            Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-Role">OLAC Role
            Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="TGN">Getty Thesaurus of Geographical
            Terms.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabulary/tgn/index.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="OLAC-WP">White Paper on Establishing an Infrastructure for Open
         Language
            Archiving<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/docs/white-paper.html</url>&gt;</ref>

      <ref abbrev="W3CDTF">Date and Time Formats, W3C
            Note.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-datetime</url>&gt;</ref>
   	
      <ref abbrev="OAI-DC">Schema for OAI implementation of Dublin Core
            metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/1.1/dc.xsd</url>&gt;</ref>

   </references>
</OLAC_doc>
