<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../OLAC_doc.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE OLAC_doc SYSTEM "../OLAC_doc.dtd">
<OLAC_doc>
	<header>
		<status code="draft" type="informational"/>
		<title>OLAC Metadata Usage Guidelines</title>
		<baseName>usage</baseName>
		<issued>20071101</issued>
		<previousIssued/>
		<abstract>
			<p>This document provides guidelines on the meaning and proper usage of the metadata elements used in the
				metadata standard of the Open Language Archives Community.</p>
		</abstract>
		<editors>Gary Simons, SIL International (<url>mailto:gary_simons@sil.org</url>)<br/>Steven Bird, University of
			Pennsylvania (<url>mailto:sb@ldc.upenn.edu</url>)</editors>
		<copyright>2007 Gary Simons (SIL International) and Steven Bird (University of Pennsylvania)</copyright>
		<changes/>
	</header>
	<body>
		<section>
			<heading>Introduction</heading>
			<p>This document provides guidelines on how to describe language resources using the OLAC metadata standard
					<cit>OLAC-Metadata</cit>. The standard itself documents the formal syntax of valid metadata records,
				but does not explain or exemplify the use of the individual metadata elements. That is the purpose of
				this document. </p>
			<p>Section 2 below describes the usage of the attributes that may be used on metadata elements. Section 3
				then describes usage in the OLAC context for the fifteen core elements of the Dublin Core metadata set.
				Section 4 describes other elements that may be used..</p>
		</section>
		<section>
			<heading>All elements</heading>
			<p>Four attributes&#8212;<i>refine, code, scheme,</i> and <i>lang</i>&#8212;are used throughout the
				XML implementation of the metadata elements. A fifth attribute, <i>langs,</i> is used on complete
				metadata records. These are described in turn below.</p>
			<p> Some elements in the OLAC metadata set use the <i>refine</i> attribute to identify element refinements.
				These qualifiers make the meaning of an element narrower or more specific. A refined element shares the
				meaning of the unqualified element, but with a more restricted scope <cit>DC-Q</cit>. When an element
				does use a <i>refine</i> attribute, the possible values for the attribute are restricted to a specified
				controlled vocabulary.</p>
			<p>Some elements in the OLAC metadata set use the <i>code</i> attribute to hold metadata values that are
				taken from a specific encoding scheme. The attribute value is always a precise value taken from a
				controlled vocabulary or a formal notation that is described in another OLAC document. As a result, all
				service providers are able to interpret uniformly the meaning of any <i>code</i> value. The terms of a
				controlled vocabulary are also incorporated into the XML schema for OLAC metadata; thus every
				<i>code</i> value is tested for validity when the OLAC registration server tests a data provider for
				conformance to OLAC standards <cit>OLAC-Registration</cit>. For elements that have a <i>code</i>
				attribute, the element content may also be used to specify a freeform elaboration of the coded value.</p>
			<p>Every element in the OLAC metadata set may use the <i>scheme</i> attribute. It specifies a standardized
				name for the scheme that constrains how the text in the content of the element is encoded. A scheme may
				be a controlled vocabulary or a formal notation. Recommended best practice is to confine the value of
					<i>scheme</i> to the label for one of the encoding schemes registered with the Dublin Core Metadata
				Initiative <cit>DCMI-Registry</cit>. Members of the OLAC community who want to use an unregistered
				scheme should submit it for registration <cit>DCMI-Submit</cit>. When OLAC data providers are tested for
				conformance to OLAC recommended best practice, only the value of the <i>scheme</i> attribute is tested
				for inclusion in the list of registered schemes. OLAC does not test the actual element content for
				conformance to the scheme; a service provider for a subcommunity that has developed a particular scheme
				could perform such a test. </p>
			<p>Every element in the OLAC metadata set may use the <i>lang</i> attribute. It specifies the language in
				which the text in the content of the element is written. The value for the attribute comes from the
				controlled vocabulary defined by <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>. By default, the <i>lang</i> attribute has the
				value "en", for English. Whenever the language of the element content is other than English, recommended
				best practice is to use the <i>lang</i> attribute to identify the language. By using multiple instances
				of the metadata elements tagged for different languages, data providers may offer their metadata records
				in multiple languages. </p>
			<p>The <i>langs</i> attribute is used on the <tt>&lt;olac&gt;</tt> element&#8212;the container
				for all the metadata elements of a given metadata record. It lists the languages in which the metadata
				record is designed to be read. This attribute holds a space-delimited list of language codes from the
					<cit>OLAC-Language</cit> controlled vocabulary. By default, this attribute has the value "en", for
				English, indicating that the record is aimed only at English readers. If an explicit value is given for
				the attribute, then the record is aimed at readers of all the languages listed.</p>
			<p>Service providers should use this information in order to offer localized views of the metadata. When a
				metadata record lists only one language, then all elements should be displayed (regardless of their
				individual languages), unless the user has requested to suppress all records in that language. When a
				metadata record has multiple alternative languages, the user should be able to select one and have
				display of elements in the other languages suppressed. An element in a language not included in the list
				of alternatives should always be displayed (for instance, the vernacular title of a work).</p>
			<p>In a given metadata record, every element is optional and every element except the
					<tt>&lt;title&gt;</tt> element is repeatable.</p>
			<element name="All elements">
				<definition><!-- Don't use. Just a trick to make export to RED/bpr.xml work. --></definition>
				<comment><!-- Ditto. --></comment>
				<bp>
					<p>Minimal best practice is for the value of each metadata element to conform to the definition of
						that element.</p>
					<p>When the meaning of a particular element in a metadata record fits the definition of a
						refinement, recommended best practice is to use the refinement rather than the generic element.</p>
					<p>Whenever the language of the element content is other than English, recommended best practice is
						to use the <i>xml:lang</i> attribute with a value from <cit>ISO639-3</cit> to identify the
						language.</p>
					<p>When a resource has more than one value for a particular metadata element, recommended best
						practice is to use a separate instance of the metadata element for each instance rather than
						listing all the values in a single instance.</p>
				</bp>
				<examples><!-- I think we want to put these here --></examples>
			</element>

		</section>
		<section>
			<heading>Individual elements</heading>
			<p>Each of the core elements of the Dublin Core metadata set is described in one of the following
				subsections. The heading gives the name of the element; the element is then described under six
				subheadings. <i>Definition</i> is the definition for the element as given by the Dublin Core Metadata
				Initiative <cit>DCMT</cit>. <i>Refinements</i> lists the refined element names (from the <i>dcterms</i>
				namespace) that may be used in place of the generic element name to specify a more precise meaning for
				the metadata item. The refinement definitions are copied from <cit>DCMT</cit>. <i>Schemes</i> lists the
				encoding schemes that may be used with this element (or its refinements) as the value of the
				<i>xsi:type</i> attribute. <i>Best practices</i> lists the best practices for the use of this element
				that are recommended by the OLAC community <cit>OLAC-BP</cit>. <i>Usage notes</i> offers additional
				notes for the OLAC community on how to use the element in the context of describing language resources.
					<i>Examples</i> shows samples of properly encoded elements and sample refinements.</p>
			<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
			<p>For many elements, you can have more than one instance. This would be the case for a work with more than
				one author, or for which you want to specify two or three languages, multiple subject terms, etc. In
				such cases, repeat the element for each person, language, etc., rather than placing all of them in a
				single instance of the field. Most elements can be repeated if needed.</p>
			<element name="Contributor">
				<definition>An entity responsible for making contributions to the resource.</definition>
				<comment>

					<p>A Contributor may be a person, an organization, or a service. Contributor is closely related to
						<xref>Creator</xref>.  A case for distinguishing the usage of the two elements can be made based on
						the degree of responsibility for the content. The Contributor designation can be used for those 
						entities whose role in the creation of the resource is not great enough to merit 
						recognition as a primary source of the intellectual content. Thus, the Contributor element  
						would be used to identify institutions that sponsored or funded the work, or to
						identify individuals who played a secondary role in the development of the
						resource (e.g., roles such as consultant, depositor, responder). The Creator element 
						would be used to identify individuals or group entities that are primarily responsible 
						for the intellectual content (e.g., roles such as author, performer).</p>
					<p>The application of the olac:role schema with its more precise vocabulary makes drawing 
						a distinction between the less precise concepts of Contributor and Creator of much less 
						significance. Thus, an alternative to making the above distinction between 
						Contributor and Creator is to use only the Contributor element, always specifying the 
						more precise nature of the contribution through the use of the olac:role vocabulary 
						(as is recommended best practice in any case).</p>
					<p>Contributor and <xref>Publisher</xref> are also somewhat related elements. In particular, the olac:role
						"sponsor" can come close to one aspect of participation that a publisher may have in regard to making
						a given resource available to the public. The olac:role "editor" is frequently one of the individual
						tasks that are collectively performed by the publisher of a work. A "sponsor" that is not also the 
						formal publisher of a resource may be entered in a Contributor element (with the proper olac:role
						specified), but the publisher should not be repeated in a Contributor element.</p>
					<p>Do not use quotation marks to enclose corporate names. If the name is a translation from its
						usual form or is not usually given in English, use the lang attribute.</p>
					<p>Be consistent with corporate name forms. Names that include a primary unit and subsidiary unit
						should be ordered with the primary unit given first. Location should generally be omitted from
						the name unless location is an integral part of the proper name of the unit.
						<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>

				</comment>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>olac:role</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The olac:role code is optionally used to specify the role (such as transcriber,
								sponsor, and so on) played by the named entity in the creation of the resource. The role
								is expressed by means of a controlled vocabulary; see <cit>OLAC-Role</cit> for the
								definition of the vocabulary. </p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>Recommended best practice is to identify the entity by means of a name in a form that is ready
						for sorting within an index. For the names of persons, this means that the name should be given
						in surname first, in inverted order (for western and other names generally written with the
						family name last). For the names of organizations, this means that any initial article should be
						omitted. </p>
					<p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>olac:role</i> scheme to indicate the role of the
						contributor.</p>
				</bp>
				<examples>
					<p>A generic contributor:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:contributor&gt;Smith, John L.&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
					<p>A funding agency:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:contributor xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="sponsor"&gt;Smithsonian Institution. Office of Fellowships and Grants.&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
					<p>The person who performed a role for which there is not a suitable code:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:contributor&gt;Smith, John L. (format conversion)&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
					<p>A corporate name given in a language differing from the majority of the metadata record:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:contributor xml:lang="ces"&gt;Česká akademie věd a	umění&lt;/dc:contributor&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
			</element>
			<element name="Coverage">
				<definition>The spatial or temporal topic of the resource, the spatial applicability of the resource, or
					the jurisdiction under which the resource is relevant.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p> Coverage will typically include spatial location (a place name or geographic coordinates),
						temporal period (a period label, date, or date range) or jurisdiction (such as a named
						administrative entity). <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
					<p>Coverage is related to <xref>Subject</xref> in having a topical orientation. Coverage in its 
						temporal aspect should not be confused with <xref>Date</xref> or one of its refinements
						(e.g., created, or available). Thus, a data set that was compiled over an extended 
						period of time should be described via <tt>dcterms:created</tt> whose content is a date 
						range, rather than with Coverage or <tt>dcterms:temporal</tt>. A data set (or any kind of resource)
						that contains or addresses historical information would correctly use Coverage or 
						<tt>dcterms:temporal</tt> to specify the date, date range or period in focus.</p>
					<p>In the OLAC context, service providers already have a database that maps languages to the
						countries in which they are spoken <cit>OLAC-Language</cit>. Coverage should not be used to
						duplicate this information; rather service providers will support searches concerning languages
						spoken in a given country by referring to the language database. Coverage should be used
						geographically only when the language involved has a wide distribution and the resource focuses
						on its use in a particular region or geopolitical jurisdiction, or conversely, when the resource
						deals with a topic of study in which the region itself is in focus, e.g., multilingualism,
						language polilcy, languages in contact, in a given locale.</p>
					<p></p>
				</comment>
				<refinements>
					<dl>
						<dt>spatial</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Spatial characteristics of the intellectual content of the resource.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>temporal</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Temporal characteristics of the intellectual content of the resource.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</refinements>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>dcterms:Box</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The DCMI Box identifies a region of space using its geographic limits
								<cit>DCMI-Box</cit>.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>dcterms:Period</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>A specification of the limits of a time interval <cit>DCMI-Period</cit></p>
						</dd>
						<dt>dcterms:Point</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The DCMI Point identifies a point in space using its geographic coordinates
									<cit>DCMI-Point</cit>.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>dcterms:TGN</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names <cit>TGN</cit>.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>In the case of Spatial coverage, recommended best practice is to use an encoding scheme to give
						precise geocoding of the resource.</p>
				</bp>


				<examples>
					<p>A resource about English in India:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:ISO639" olac:code="en"/&gt;&lt;dcterms:spatial&gt;India&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
					<p>A resource about languages spoken on Guadalcanal:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dcterms:spatial xsi:type="dcterms:TGN"&gt;Guadalcanal	(island)&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
					<p>A resource about language use in the 19th century:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dcterms:temporal&gt;19th century&lt;/dcterms:temporal&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
			</element>
			<element name="Creator">
				<definition>An entity primarily responsible for making the resource.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p>A Creator may be a person, an organization, or a service. Creator is closely related to
						<xref>Contributor</xref>. Creator may be differentiated from Contributor based on the degree of
						involvement as a primary source of the intellectual content. In determining whether an entity
						is a Creator (as opposed to a Contributor), consider the role in the creation of the resource, 
						using the same criteria that are followed for deciding that an entity should be
						listed as an "author" in a bibliographic reference of the resource. Entities that do not merit 
						that level of recognition should be treated as Contributors.</p>					
					<p>The application of the olac:role schema with its more precise vocabulary makes drawing 
						a distinction between the less precise concepts of Contributor and Creator of much less 
						significant. Thus, an alternative to making the above distinction between 
						Contributor and Creator is to use only the Contributor element, always specifying the 
						more precise nature of the contribution through the use of the olac:role vocabulary 
						(as is recommended best practice in any case).</p>

				</comment>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>olac:role</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The <i>refine</i> attribute is optionally used to specify the role (such as author,
								editor, translator, and so on) played by the named entity in the creation of the
								resource. The role is expressed by means of a controlled vocabulary; see
								<cit>OLAC-Role</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. </p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>Recommended best practice is to identify a Creator by means of a name in a form that is ready for
						sorting within an index. For the names of persons, this means that the name should be given in
						with the surname first (an "inverted" order for most Western name forms). For the names of 
						organizations, this means that any initial article should be omitted. </p>
					<p>Recommended best practice is to use the <i>olac:role</i> scheme to indicate the role of the
						creator.</p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>A personal author:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:creator&gt;Bloomfield, Leonard&lt;/dc:creator&gt;</eg>
					<p>An institutional author:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:creator&gt;Linguistic Society of America&lt;/dc:creator&gt;</eg>
					<p>An editor:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:creator xsi:type="olac:role" olac:code="editor"&gt;Sapir, Edward&lt;/dc:creator&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
				<todo>
					<p>Here, and with Contributor, we recommend a format that puts surname first. Are there other
						name-related standards in AACR2 that we should recommend? We need help from a librarian to give
						us a synopsis (or a pointer to such) of the rules for fomatting personal and corporate names.
					</p>
				</todo>
			</element>
			<element name="Date">
				<definition>A point or period of time associated with an event in the lifecycle of the resource.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p>A Date with no refinement will be assumed to be the date of issue (i.e. publication). 
						Date of publication may differ from its creation date; thus it can be helpful to prospective users
						to include more than one kind of Date element (refinement). However, a single resource
						should not have more than one instance of each date refinement, with the possible exception of
						<tt>dcterms:modified</tt>. Where the modification history of a resource is significant, it is 
						appropriate to enter this information in a <xref>Provenance</xref> element, which allows 
						for explanation of modifications in a way that <tt>dcterms:modified</tt> does not.</p>
					<p>‘Available’ as a refinement pertains to Date, not to other aspects of availability.</p>
					<p>Do not use additional terms such as “recorded on” or “donated on” in the element text.</p>
				</comment>
				<refinements>
					<dl>
						<dt>available</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Date (often a range) that the resource will become or did become available.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>created</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Date of creation of the resource.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>dateAccepted</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Date of acceptance of the resource (e.g. of thesis by university department, of article
								by journal, etc.).</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>dateCopyrighted</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Date of a statement of copyright.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>dateSubmitted</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Date of submission of the resource (e.g. thesis, articles, etc.).</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>issued</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Date of formal issuance (e.g., publication) of the resource.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>modified</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Date on which the resource was changed.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>valid</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Date (often a range) of validity of a resource.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</refinements>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>dcterms:W3CDTF</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>W3C Encoding rules for dates and times - a profile based on ISO 8601
							<cit>W3CDTF</cit>.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>Recommended minimal best practice is that a record have at least one instance of Date (or one of its
						refinements).</p>
					<p>Recommended best practice is that every instance of Date (or a refinement) use the
						<i>dcterms:W3CDTF</i> scheme, or enclose the element value in square brackets if the value does
						not conform to the encoding scheme (e.g., if it is supplied by the cataloger, is approximate or
						is in some doubt). A WSCDTF-conformant value may be for the year alone, for the year and month, or for 
						an exact date. A range of years is also a valid value; in this case both years 
						must be four-digit values and the earliest year should come first. Thus, the element value 
						may match one of the four following patterns: <tt>YYYY</tt>, <tt>YYYY-MM</tt>, 
						<tt>YYYY-MM-DD</tt>, or <tt>YYYY-YYYY</tt>.</p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>A typical year of publication:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:date xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">1992"&lt;/dc:date&gt;</eg>
					<p>A resource modified on October 16, 1996:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dcterms:modified xsi:type="dcterms:W3CDTF">1996-10-16&lt;/dcterms:modified&gt;</eg>
					<p>A resource from approximately 1950:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:date>circa 1950&lt;/dc:date&gt;</eg>
					<p>A resource for which the date has been supplied by the cataloger from external informaiton:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:date>[1932]&lt;/dc:date&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
			</element>
			<element name="Description">
				<definition>An account of the resource.</definition>
				<comment>

					<p>Description may include but is not limited to: an abstract, table of contents, reference to a
						graphical representation of content, or a free-text summary account of the content.
						<cit>DCMT</cit></p>
					<p>Description may also offer an annotation, or a qualitative or evaluative comment about the
						resource, such as a statement about suitability for a particular application or context.</p>
					<p> Description element is not a "catch-all" category. The Description element should not be
						confused with Subject. Description contains free-text (prose) statements, while Subject contains
						subject headings, faceted terms, or specific subject descriptors, e.g., Library of Congress
						Subject Headings, or Linguistics and Language Behavior Abstracts thesaurus descriptors.
						Description should likewise not be used in place of Extent to contain information solely about
						the length, duration, or size of a work.</p>
					<p>No formatting conventions are defined within the text of Description. Service providers may
						format the entire Description as a single paragraph, collapsing adjacent white space characters
						into a single space.</p>
					<p>When there is a URL for a document that describes the resource, use a separate Description
						element to encode just that URL. A Description that begins with "http:" will be interpreted by
						service providers as consisting solely of a URL and will be presented as a link in user
						interfaces. Service providers are not obliged to search other Description text for the
						occurrence of URLs.</p>
				</comment>
				<refinements>
					<dl>
						<dt>abstract</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>A summary of the content of the resource.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>tableOfContents</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>A list of subunits of the content of the resource.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</refinements>
				<bp>

					<p>Recommended best practice is that a metadata record should contain at least one Description (or one
						of its refinements or Subject element. While these are different in purpose and content (see
						Usage Notes below), they both nevertheless give the prospective user some idea of the content of
						the resource that goes beyond the informative potential of just a title alone. Using both
						Description and subject elements is encouraged.</p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>A prose description of a resource:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:description&gt;The CALLHOME Japanese corpus of telephone speech consists of 120
   unscripted telephone conversations between native speakers of Japanese. All calls, which lasted
   up to 30 minutes, originated in North America and were placed to locations overseas (typically
   Japan). Most participants called family members or close friends. This corpus contains speech
   data files ONLY, along with the minimal amount of documentation needed to describe the contents
   and format of the speech files and the software packages needed to uncompress the speech data.
   &lt;/dc:description&gt;</eg>
					<p>A contents note for a resource:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dcterms:tableOfContents&gt;v. 1: Thesaurus of Khmu dialects in Southeast Asia; v. 2:
   Dictionary of Khmu in China; v. 3: Dictionary of Khmu in Laos; v. 4: Dictionary of Khmu in
   Vietnam; v. 5: Dictionary of Khmu in Thailand&lt;/dcterms:tableOfContents&gt;</eg>
					<p>A reference to an existing on-line description:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:description&gt;http://www.ldc.upenn.edu/Catalog/LDC96S37.html&lt;/dc:description&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
			</element>
			<element name="Format">
				<definition>The file format, physical medium, or dimensions of the resource.</definition>
				<comment>

					<p>Typically, Format may include the media-type, physical material, and/or dimensions of the
						resource. Format may be used to determine the software, hardware or other equipment needed to
						display or operate the resource. Examples of dimensions include size and duration.
						<cit>DCMT</cit></p>
					<p>In the case of a physical object, the refinements medium and extent are most applicable. These
						may respectively contain the physical material of the object (e.g., parchment; reel-to-reel
						tape; 35 mm slide; NTSC encoded VHS cassette), and the size/duration (e.g. number of pages and
						dimensions of a book; length of a recording).</p>
					<!-- paraphrase from PARK_IMLS.pdf -->
					<p>Format (and its refinement 'medium'), which encompasses the notion of physical media categories 
						such as photograph, should not be confused with <xref>Type</xref>, which categorizes the 
						nature or genre of the content of the resource based on the mode in which the user 
						experiences or interacts with the resource, and as such includes terms that describe general 
						categories, functions, or aggregation levels for content.</p>
					<!--<p>OLAC had 5 refinements (cpu, encoding, markup, os, sourcecode) but each of these was used very
						little, if at all  http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf    </p> -->

				</comment>
				<refinements>
					<dl>
						<dt>extent</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The size or duration of the resource.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>medium</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The material or physical carrier of the resource.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</refinements>

				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>dcterms:IMT</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The Internet media type of the resource.<cit>IMT</cit>.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>In the case of a digital resource, recommended best practice is to express the format using a
						MIME type from the <i>dcterms:IMT</i> scheme. </p>
				</bp>
				<examples>
					<p>For a digitally encoded dictionary:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;text/xml&lt;/dc:format&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:extent&gt;5,237 entries in a 1.2M XML file.&lt;/dcterms:extent&gt;</eg>
					<p>For a digitally recorded text:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:format xsi:type="dcterms:IMT"&gt;audio/wav&lt;/dc:format&gt;
   &lt;dc:format&gt;Sampling: 1 channel, 22 KHz, 8 bits.&lt;/dc:format&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:extent&gt;Duration: 153 seconds. Size: 3.3M. &lt;/dcterms:extent&gt;</eg>
					<p>For 16mm film with sound track</p>
					<eg>&lt;dcterms:medium&gt;sound, color;  16mm film&lt;/dcterms:medium&gt;
   &lt;dcterms:extent&gt;30 min.&lt;/dcterms:extent&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
			</element>
			<!-- Identifier would probably benefit from a more thorough best practice document.  -->
			<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf -->
			<element name="Identifier">
				<definition>An unambiguous reference to the resource within a given context.</definition>
				<comment>

					<p>In the case of a resource that is not electronically encoded, but is housed in a conventional
						archive, Identifier may be used to give a local shelf or box number, or whatever scheme is used
						to locate a resource within the collection.</p>
					<p>Identifiers that begin with "http:" will be interpreted by service providers as URLs and be
						presented as links in user interfaces. Complete relative link paths with the base server so that
						the link will be valid outside the search system of the host archives.</p>
					<p>Identifier is of particular value in enabling other resources to unambiguously refer to the
						resource in focus in terms of a specific relationship. See <xref>Relation</xref> for best
						practice and usage notes in creating relationship links between resources.</p>
					<p>A unique identifier that has been assigned to a digital resource by the researcher, a research
						organization or department, or an archives or library for internal reference may continue to be
						useful in identifying the resource alongside a URI assigned in the context of a digital
						repository. Such a unique identifier may be significant for continuity of identification for a
						digital resource throughout its lifecycle, as other resources may have used such an identifier
						in referencing the object prior to the assignment of the URI later in its lifecycle.</p>
					<p>Do not specify the "oai:" identifier for the resource itself as a value of Identifier, since it
						is already given in <tt>&lt;identifier&gt;</tt> in the <tt>&lt;header&gt;</tt>
						of the <tt>&lt;record&gt;</tt>s returned by the OAI protocol.</p>
					<p>Do not use Identifier for a URL intended to direct the searcher to a <xref>Description</xref>,
						availability or usage or other <xref>Rights</xref>-related information. A URI may be used in
						each of those elements or refinements to link to such information. Likewise, Identifier should
						not be used to refer to a general collection site in which the resource is one of many works
						available.</p>

				</comment>
				<refinements>
					<dl>
						<dt>bibliographicCitation</dt>
						<dd>

							<p>A bibliographic reference for the resource. Comment: Recommended practice is to include
								sufficient bibliographic detail to identify the resource as unambiguously as possible,
								whether or not the citation is in a standard form. </p>

							<p>A bibliographic reference for the resource. </p>

						</dd>
					</dl>
				</refinements>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>A URI Uniform Resource Identifier.<cit>URI</cit>.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>Recommended best practice is to specify the <i>dcterms;URI</i> scheme when the value is a Uniform
						Resource Locator (URL).</p>
					<p>Recommended practice for a bibliographic citation is to include sufficient bibliographic detail
						to identify the resource as unambiguously as possible, whether or not the citation is in a
						standard form.</p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>A Uniform Resource Locator for retrieval of an electronically encoded resource:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:identifier xsi:type="dcterms:URI"&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/cs.CL/0010033&lt;/dc:identifier&gt;</eg>
					<p>A local identifier for retrieval within a physical collection:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:identifier&gt;Series: A, Box 7&lt;/dc:identifier&gt;</eg>
					<p>The citation for a chapter that was published in a book:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dcterms:bibliographicCitation&gt;In Joel Sherzer and Greg Urban (eds.), Native South
American discourse, 237-306. Berlin: Mouton. &lt;dcterms:bibliographicCitation&gt;</eg>

				</examples>
			</element>
			<element name="Language">
				<definition>A language of the resource.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p>Language is used for a language the resource is in, as opposed to the language it describes (see
							<xref>Subject.language</xref>). It is related to the audience for the work in that it
						identifies a language that the creator of the resource assumes that its eventual user will
						understand. When a resource is in more than one language, use a separate Language element for
						each language.</p>
					<p>For a work of literature or other monolingual document aimed at the speakers of a particular
						language, use Language to identify that language. For a sound recording, use Language for the
						language being spoken in the recording. For a grammatical description, for instance, use
						Language for the language the grammar is written in; use Subject.language for the language whose
						grammar is being described. For an annotated text, use Language for the language in which the
						annotations are made; use Subject.language for the language of the base text that is being
						annotated. For a dictionary, use Language for the language in which the definitions are written;
						use Subject.language for the language whose words are being defined.</p>
					<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
					<p>For scholarly works, this will usually be a major language (English, French, Indonesian, etc.).
						For vernacular works, it will be the minority language and will usually be the same as the
						language coded in subject_language. Repeat tag for each code needed for polyglot works. Give the
						language name in this element, if it is a specific variety of the language as identified using
						its three-letter ISO 6390-3 identifier, which should be given in \language_code.</p>
					<!-- Following from Joan Spanne's SIL_Guidelines. -->
					<p>PLEASE make an effort to use and keep up to date the Ethnologue code identification of
						collections, rather than using an entity developed code for individual languages, as entity
						specific codes become confusing or misleading when removed from the immediate entity context.</p>
					<p>May need to clarify between language name or code and attribute supplying OLAC language code.
						<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
				</comment>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>olac:ISO639-3</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The ISO 639-3 set of three-letter identifiers for the identification of human languages.
								See <cit>OLAC-Language</cit> for the definition of the vocabulary. </p>
							<!-- Move to a <bp><p>? -->
							<p>Recommended best practice is to specify the language via the <i>code</i> attribute while
								leaving the element content empty. Use the element content only when the controlled
								vocabulary does not offer an appropriate code, or when further specification is needed,
								such as to name a specific dialect or to give an alternate name that differs from the
								default name given by the controlled vocabulary. </p>
							<p>Service providers should use the <i>code</i> attribute to support searches by language,
								and may use the element content in searches by keyword. They also may supply the default
								language name in keyword searching when the element content is missing.</p>
							<!-- What about md-lang from OLACSIL.txt ? -->
							<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
							<p> \desc The language in which this metadata record is primarily written (not including
								coded range-set values). Multiple titles (using alternative), descriptions, and subject
								terms may be given in additional languages to aid in searching; specify the language
								used for each of those if different from the language specified in this element. </p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>Minimal best practice is that every record contain at least one Language element.</p>
					<p>Minimal best practice is that every Language element use the <i>olac:ISO639-3</i> scheme to
						identify it precisely.</p>
					<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
					<p>[For more than one language repeat the] \language and \subject_language [elements], which have
						sub-elements for ISO code language identifiers.</p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>A resource in English about the Sikaiana language:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="eng"/&gt; &lt;dc:subject
						xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="sky"/&gt;</eg>
					<p>A Yemba-French dictionary, where the alternate name Dschang is preferred.</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="fra"/&gt; &lt;dc:subject
						xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="ybb"&gt;Dschang&lt;/dc:language&gt;</eg>
					<p>The <i>American Heritage Dictionary</i>, which is both in and about American English:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:language xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="eng"/&gt; &lt;dc:subject
						xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="eng"/&gt; &lt;dcterms:spatial&gt;United
						States&lt;/dcterms:spatial&gt;</eg>
					<p>A resource about a language for which the controlled vocabulary does not yet provide a code:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="olac:language"&gt;Ancient
					Sumerian&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
				<todo>
					<p>Add an example of specifying a dialect.</p>
					<p>Do we want olac:ISO639-3 (analogous to dcterms:ISO639-2) or olac:language so that we can use it
						without a code?</p>
					<p>Write the OLAC-Language document.</p>
				</todo>
			</element>
			<element name="Provenance">
				<!-- Provenance is not in "Section 2: The Dublin Core Metadata Element Set" at http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/.  It is found in "Section 3: Other Elements and Element Refinements" -->
				<definition>A statement of any changes in ownership and custody of the resource since its creation that
					are significant for its authenticity, integrity and interpretation.</definition>
				<comment>
					<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 48 -->
					<p>PROVENANCE: 1) The individual, department or agency that created, accumulated, maintained and/or
						used materials (data sources, documents). 2) Information regarding the origin and custodial
						history of documents or data sources. The Principle of Provenance (also known as “respect des
						fonds”), a foundational principle of archives management, is that materials of the same
						provenance must not be intermingled with those of any other provenance. It is the principle of
						provenance that is the basis for arranging and storing materials by language project (as the
						original setting of creation and accumulation), rather than extracting and collocating all
						grammar materials, all anthropology materials, all instances of a shell book, etc. into topical
						collections in the archives.</p>
					<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 17-->

					<p>Unlike a library, which usually organizes works by topic, the archive should organize materials
						by common origin or provenance.... In general, it is best to keep collections together as a
						physical unit (as much as the different types of media permit), with each language program
						collection stored on its own computer media unit (such as CD-R), or all together in adjacent
						paper files. This most easily enables a particular team to see what has been submitted in the
						past and maintains the physical integrity of each collection consistently for archives
						management procedures.... the archives should not mix materials from different
						collections...according to...topical categories.</p>
					<p><!-- from PARK_KO.pdf -->The most frequently identified of all locally added metadata elements,
						concern provenance information such as: ‘contact information’, ‘ordering information’, and
						‘acquisition.’</p>

					<p>Unlike a library, which usually organizes works by topic, the archive should organize materials
						by common origin or provenance.... In general, it is best to keep collections together as a
						physical unit (as much as the different types of media permit), with each language program
						collection stored on its own computer media unit (such as CD-R), or all together in adjacent
						paper files. This most easily enables a particular team to see what has been submitted in the
						past and maintains the physical integrity of each collection consistently for archives
						management procedures.... the archives should not mix materials from different
						collections...according to...topical categories.</p>
					<p><!-- from PARK_KO.pdf -->The most frequently identified all locally added metadata elements,
						concern provenance information such as: ‘contact information’, ‘ordering information’, and
						‘acquisition.’</p>

				</comment>
			</element>
			<element name="Publisher">
				<definition>An entity responsible for making the resource available.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p>Examples of a Publisher include a person, an organization, or a service. Typically, the name of a
						Publisher should be used to indicate the entity. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
					<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 35 -->
					<p>Content (documents, web pages—text, graphics, streaming audio and video) created for and
						published on the World Wide Web on a sanctioned entity site comprises a special class of
						published materials. Web content of a more document-like nature (a specific title, a credited
						author, and a date), such as an electronic working paper series, should be archived, and can
						usually be handled similarly to a print publication. Articles written by SIL authors for
						electronic journals or other formal web publications on other web sites should also be archived.
						Materials initially published in print (or on audio cassette, etc.) and converted for the web
						should be elsewhere included in the archives collection, though the new computer form (PDF,
						HTML, MP3) might also be suitable for maintaining as a presentation form.</p>
					<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 35 on advisability of including UNPUBLISHED materials -->
					<p>Caring for unpublished resources of long term value ... Language data, either in lexical form (a
						database) or as a text (with documentation) is more and more sought after as input for
						computational linguistic analysis. Descriptions and analyses are also desirable, if they are of
						reasonably good quality (e.g. consultant checked). Translation by-products, such as key terms
						papers and back translations, can be very useful to other teams in related languages. Language
						surveys and their supporting data are very valuable. Collected texts, recorded language data and
						transcriptions, if of sufficiently good quality, are also very valuable, as are photographs and
						slides, but the complexities resulting from lack of context (if not well documented) and ethical
						considerations add to the challenges of managing them in the archives .</p>
					<p>Being selective about what should be archived is important. Selectivity imposes an extra initial
						labor cost, but one which pays dividends in the short and long runs. For the submitter, being
						selective reduces the amount of material submitted, and therefore, reduces the burden of
						describing the material as well. For the archives, every object has a cost of storage, migration
						and management, which is balanced against its short and long term value. Is this a work that
						will be useful or informative in the future? Is it unique? Is it something that can no longer be
						obtained elsewhere? Is it reasonably good quality? ‘Yes’ to these indicates that a work is
						probably worth keeping.</p>
					<p>Usually a publisher or the archives itself, sometimes with URL, sometimes URL given in separate
						instance of element. Do not use it for host publication information, which should be in
						Relation.<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
					<p><!-- from Park_KO.pdf -->Semantic overlap engenders confusion and inaccuracy in the usage of the
						DC metadata elements Creator, Contributor and Publisher.</p>
					<p><!-- from Park_KO.pdf -->Semantic overlap engenders confusion and inaccuracy in the usage of the
						DC metadata elements Creator, Contributor and Publisher.</p>

				</comment>
				<bp>
					<p>Recommended best practice is to identify a Publisher by means of a name in a form that is ready
						for sorting within an index. For the names of persons, this means that the name should be given
						in inverted order with the surname first. For the names of organizations, this means that any
						initial article should be omitted.</p>
					<p>Copyright statement should be in text of element, not in the ‘code’
						<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
					<p>Rights developments: – With the Access extension on Rights, OLAC is integrating access and
						permitted use – Leave the work to the content of the element or a referral to additional
						information</p>
					<p>Additional good practice guidance is needed regarding parameters of protection: duration of
						restriction, entity with authority to override, expectations placed on users
						<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
					<p>– Identifier was used (repeated) for what clearly had to be a Source resource URL (based on
						contextual content of record) – Source was used to give information on the linguistic
						consultant, with lengthy description. The whole would have been more appropriate in Description
						element. (Contributor was used also) – Source was used to specify an entity responsible for
						development, creation, donation, etc. of the resource (in one a Ph.D. granting institution is
						named, another the gov. agency responsible, others, SIL is named)
						<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf -->
					</p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>A typical publisher:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:publisher&gt;Oxford University Press&lt;/dc:publisher&gt;</eg>
					<p>The URL for a publisher:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:publisher
						xsi:type="dcterms:URI"&gt;http://www.oup.com&lt;/dc:publisher&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
			</element>
			<element name="Relation">
				<definition>A related resource.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p>This element is used to document relationships between resources, for instance, part-whole
						relationships, version relationships, dependency relationships, and so on. When the related
						resource is also in a participating archive, the reference to the related resource should be by
						means of an "oai:" identifier. A Relation that begins with "oai:" should be presented by service
						providers as an active link that retrieves the metadata for that resource.</p>
					<p>For a required markup definition (like a DTD or Schema) use <xref>Format.markup</xref> rather
						than Relation. When the required software or hardware can be inferred from the
						<xref>Format</xref> of the resource, do not also use Relation for this purpose.</p>
					<p>When the present resource is a derived work, the source resource is typically indicated by
							<xref>Source</xref>. However, there are two cases in which refinements of Relation are used
						for derived works. The <i>isVersionOf</i> refinement is used when the present resource is a new
						version or edition with added intellectual content that has been developed by the same creators.
						When the new version is nothing more than a rendition in a new format, then the
						<i>isForrmatOf</i> refinement is used. </p>
					<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
					<p>Use this element to associate independent but conceptually related materials. Use the
						\relationType element to specify the nature of the relationship between the work described in
						this record and the work whose ID is given in this element. Repeat for each related item. Use an
						unambiguous identifier (such as the \primaryid) for the related resource, if possible, or a
						standard name for a schema to which this resource conforms, e.g., GOLD: General Ontology for
						Linguistic Description.</p>
					<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 16 -->
					<p>Relationship metadata pertains to relationships among independent objects, such as print/analog
						and digital forms of the same content, presentation and source forms, a dissertation and a book
						which came directly from it. This must not be confused with the administrative metadata elements
						that link distinct but dependent parts of a largertaloger-defined field names such as 'digital
						collection,' and 'example issues.' whole.</p>
					<p>Relationship metadata pertains to relationships among independent objects, such as print/analog
						and digital forms of the same content, presentation and source forms, a dissertation and a book
						which came directly from it. This must not be confused with the administrative metadata elements
						that link distinct but dependent parts of a largertaloger-defined field names such as 'digital
						collection,' and 'example issues.' whole.</p>

					<p>“Previously” could utilize “Replaces”
						<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
					<p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_KO.pdf -->Relation may be inconsistently mapped onto various
						cataloger-defined fields. Do not use Relation interchangeably with ca</p>
				</comment>
				<refinements>
					<dl>
						<dt>conformsTo</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>A reference to an established standard to which the resource conforms.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>hasFormat</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource pre-existed the referenced resource, which is essentially the same
								intellectual content presented in another format.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>hasPart</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource includes the referenced resource either physically or
							logically.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>hasVersion</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource has a version, edition, or adaptation, namely, the referenced
								resource.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>isFormatOf</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource is the same intellectual content of the referenced resource, but
								presented in another format.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>isPartOf</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource is a physical or logical part of the referenced resource.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>isReferencedBy</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource is referenced, cited, or otherwise pointed to by the referenced
								resource.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>isReplacedBy</dt>
						<dd/>
						<dt>isRequiredBy</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource is required by the referenced resource, either physically or
								logically.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>isVersionOf</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource is a version, edition, or adaptation of the referenced resource.
								Changes in version imply substantive changes in content rather than differences in
								format.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>references</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource references, cites, or otherwise points to the referenced
							resource.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>replaces</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource supplants, displaces, or supersedes the referenced resource.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>requires</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The described resource requires the referenced resource to support its function,
								delivery, or coherence of content.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</refinements>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>A URI Uniform Resource Identifier.<cit>URI</cit>.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>When the related resource is also held in a participating archive, recommended best practice is
						to identify the related resource by means of its OAI identifier. </p>
					<!-- from OLACSIL_in_Toolbox_Instructions-1 -->
					<p>In general, element properties—the labels, definitions, and range sets, should not be changed.
						However, two of the properties that may be changed are the font used for a specific field, and
						the language properties assigned to the field. This is the way that a field can be made to use a
						different (Unicode compliant) font and specific rules for word breaks, etc. that differ from
						those applied to other fields.A good candidate for customizing this way is the \title field, or
						the \alternative field. Keep in mind that all instances of that field will use the same font.
						The font should be a Unicode compliant font, not a legacy font that substitutes some characters
						with other characters (characters with different meanings, not just different representations).
						A custom font that has been developed to render Unicode characters better than or not available
						in generic Unicode fonts like Arial Unicode MS or Doulos SIL may be used. Be sure to document
						the font itself as a resource, and include it among the computer files of your collection. If
						these are foreign concepts, then don’t worry about this.</p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>A link to a required font:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dcterms:requires&gt;oai:sil:software/ipafont&lt;/dcterms:requires&gt;</eg>
					<p>Links to the component pieces of a collected work:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding126&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
						&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding127&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
						&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding128&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
						&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding129&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;
						&lt;dcterms:hasPart&gt;oai:somearchive:holding130&lt;/dcterms:hasPart&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
				<todo>
					<p>Do we need a scheme for olac:OAI to represent an OLAC OAI identifier? Or should we just use
						dcterms:URI and match on initial "oai:"?</p>
				</todo>
			</element>
			<element name="Rights">
				<definition>Information about rights held in and over the resource.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p> Typically, a Rights element will contain a rights management statement for the resource, or
						reference a service providing such information. Rights information often encompasses
						Intellectual Property Rights (IPR), Copyright, and various Property Rights. If the Rights
						element is absent, no assumptions can be made about the status of these and other rights with
						respect to the resource. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
					<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p. 12 -->
					<p>Copyrights are also inherent in primary linguistic and cultural research materials, such as
						stories, descriptions, songs or art work, which researcher collect in the course of their work.
						The rights, in most cases, belong to the creator—not the researcher or SIL—or, in some cases, to
						the language community (as a legal entity). Intellectual property law as it applies to community
						cultural property is not yet well-defined and is beyond the scope of these guidelines. However,
						documenting the creators of such works and the conditions under which they came into the hands
						of an SIL worker are critical steps in archiving these valuable works. Only with this
						information about their origins can SIL follow through on its intention to respect the
						intellectual property rights of vernacular language communities in which we work.</p>
					<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
					<p>Specify a license, access conditions (for the public) or rights holders specific to this item. A
						rights holder may be the publisher, if the author assigned rights to the work in a publication
						contract, or a member of a language community if the work is that person’s creative initiative
						and he/she was not in the employ of an entity language project. (Do not include SIL
						International, an SIL entity or a WO, as the appropriate authority is assumed based on the
						primary id.) If the Rights element is absent, no assumptions can be made about the status of
						these and other rights with respect to the resource.</p>
					<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p.26-->
					<p>Texts and recordings are collected by a language worker often based on an assumption of private
						use for research. However, they are the intellectual property of someone else. The original
						writer or speaker, or perhaps the language community as a body, might want to assert ownership
						if texts or recordings are used for a purpose besides the original collector’s private study. To
						publish or otherwise distribute these works should have the approval of the owner—the creator.
						Because of this, special documentation is needed in an archives context. For language texts it
						is wise to document the speaker’s name, basic demographic information , the context in which
						collecting took place, and the date.</p>
					<!-- from SIL_Guidelines p.26-->
					<p>Photographs, similarly, are usually taken in a context assuming private use, unless a media
						person explicitly states other intentions. Though the photograph is the intellectual property of
						the photographer, publication of a photograph with identifiable persons should take into
						consideration their privacy rights and preferences.</p>
				</comment>
				<refinements>
					<dl>
						<dt>accessRights</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Information about who can access the resource or an indication of its security status.
								Comment: Access Rights may include information regarding access or restrictions based on
								privacy, security or other regulations. </p>
						</dd>
						<dt>license</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>A legal document giving official permission to do something with the resource. Comment:
								Recommended best practice is to identify the license using a URI. Examples of such
								licenses can be found at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/. </p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</refinements>

				<todo>
					<p>Mention Creative Commons in the usage notes and give an example of a CC license statement.</p>
				</todo>
			</element>
			<element name="Rights Holder">
				<!-- Rights Holder is not in this order in the DCMI listing at http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/.  It is found in "Section 3: Other Elements and Element Refinements" (in alphabetical order). -->
				<definition>A person or organization owning or managing rights over the resource.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p>Use the URI or name of the Rights Holder to indicate the entity.</p>
				</comment>

			</element>
			<element name="Source">
				<definition>The resource from which the described resource is derived.</definition>
				<comment>
					<!-- Move to <bp><p>? -->
					<p>The present resource may be derived from the Source resource in whole or in part. <cit>DCMT</cit>
						When the Source resource is also available in an on-line archive, recommended best practice is
						to reference it by means of an "oai:" identifier. In this case service providers should
						presented the Source as an active link that retrieves the metadata for that resource. </p>
					<p> In the legal parlance of intellectual property rights, a "derivative work" is one that is based
						on one or more preexisting works. This includes cases in which a work may be recast,
						transformed, or adapted in any way, such as by translation, abridgement, dramatization,
						recording, transcription, or digital encoding. A work consisting of editorial revisions,
						annotations, elaborations, or other modifications, which, as a whole, represent an original work
						of authorship is also a derivative work <cit>Copyright</cit>.</p>
					<p>This legal definition elucidates the sense of "derived" that is intended in the Dublin Core
						definition of Source. Note, however, that this overlaps with <xref>Relation</xref>, since the
							<i>isFormatOf</i> and <i>isVersionOf</i> refinements both refer to derivative works in the
						technical sense.</p>
					<p>Use Source (as opposed to Relation) in cases when the present resource has a substantially
						different <xref>Type</xref> or <xref>Creator</xref> or <xref>Title</xref> than the Source
						resource. When the difference from the original work is only a difference of <xref>Date</xref>
						or <xref>Format</xref> or <xref>Publisher</xref> or <xref>Identifier</xref> or edition
						designator in the <xref>Title</xref>, then use Relation to encode the relationship to the
						original work.</p>
					<p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_KO.pdf -->Source may be inconsistently mapped onto various
						cataloger-defined fields. An area of confusion is the distinction between Source and Relation.</p>
					<p>The present resource may be derived from the Source resource in whole or in part. <cit>DCMT</cit>
						When the Source resource is also available in an on-line archive, recommended best practice is
						to reference it by means of an "oai:" identifier. In this case service providers should
						presented the Source as an active link that retrieves the metadata for that resource. </p>
					<p> In the legal parlance of intellectual property rights, a "derivative work" is one that is based
						on one or more preexisting works. This includes cases in which a work may be recast,
						transformed, or adapted in any way, such as by translation, abridgement, dramatization,
						recording, transcription, or digital encoding. A work consisting of editorial revisions,
						annotations, elaborations, or other modifications, which, as a whole, represent an original work
						of authorship is also a derivative work <cit>Copyright</cit>.</p>
					<p>This legal definition elucidates the sense of "derived" that is intended in the Dublin Core
						definition of Source. Note, however, that this overlaps with <xref>Relation</xref>, since the
							<i>isFormatOf</i> and <i>isVersionOf</i> refinements both refer to derivative works in the
						technical sense.</p>
					<p>Use Source (as opposed to Relation) in cases when the present resource has a substantially
						different <xref>Type</xref> or <xref>Creator</xref> or <xref>Title</xref> than the Source
						resource. When the difference from the original work is only a difference of <xref>Date</xref>
						or <xref>Format</xref> or <xref>Publisher</xref> or <xref>Identifier</xref> or edition
						designator in the <xref>Title</xref>, then use Relation to encode the relationship to the
						original work.</p>
					<p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_KO.pdf -->Source may be inconsistently mapped onto various
						cataloger-defined fields. An area of confusion is the distinction between Source and Relation.</p>


				</comment>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>dcterms:URI</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>A URI Uniform Resource Identifier.<cit>URI</cit>.</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>When the Source resource is also held in a participating archive, recommended best practice is to
						identify the related resource by means of its OAI identifier. </p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>Source for a digital encoding of a manuscript in a participating archive:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:source&gt;oai:somearchive:holding1023&lt;/dc:source&gt;</eg>
					<p>Source for data extracted from a published source:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:source&gt;Kwara'ae flora vocabulary extracted from Guide to the Forests of the
						British Solomon Islands, by T. C. Whitmore. Oxford University Press,
						1966.&lt;/dc:source&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
			</element>
			<element name="Subject">
				<definition>The topic of the resource.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p>Typically, a Subject will be expressed as keywords, key phrases or classification codes that
						describe a topic of the resource. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
					<p>To describe the spatial or temporal topic of the resource, use the <xref>Coverage</xref> element.</p>
					<p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_IMLS.pdf --> The Subject element should not be confused with
						Description. Subject contains subject headings, while Description contains free-text
						descriptions.</p>
					<p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_KO.pdf -->Avoid mapping the DC Subject element to a variety of
						cataloger-defined natural vocabularies such as 'topic', 'category', and 'keyword.'</p>
					<p><!-- paraphrase from PARK_KO.pdf -->Avoid mapping the DC Subject element to a variety of
						cataloger-defined natural vocabularies such as 'topic', 'category', and 'keyword.'</p>
				</comment>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>olac:ISO639-3</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The ISO 639-3 set of three-letter identifiers for the identification of human languages.
								See <xref>Language</xref> for a complete discussion (with examples) of using this
								scheme.</p>
							<!-- Move to a <bp><p>? -->
							<p>Recommended best practice is to specify the language via the <i>code</i> attribute while
								leaving the element content empty. Use the element content only when the controlled
								vocabulary does not offer an appropriate code, or when further specification is needed,
								such as to name a specific dialect or to give an alternate name that differs from the
								default name given by the controlled vocabulary. </p>
							<p>Service providers should use the <i>code</i> attribute to support searches by language,
								and may use the element content in searches by keyword. They also may supply the default
								language name in keyword searching when the element content is missing.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>olac:linguistic-field</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The OLAC vocabulary for describing the content of a resource as relevant to a particular
								subfield of linguistic science <cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Field</cit>. </p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>Minimal best practice is that a metadata record should contain at least one Description or
						Subject element.</p>
					<p>When the subject is a human language, minimal best practice is to use the <i>olac:ISO639-3</i>
						scheme to identify it precisely.</p>
					<p>When the subject matter falls within the field of linguistics, recommended best practice is to
						use the <i>olac:linguistic-field</i> scheme to identify the subfield.</p>
					<p><!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->Recommended best practice is to select a value from a
						controlled vocabulary or formal classification scheme, such as: DDC, or LCSH. Use to indicate
						topic or type of resource if not identified in other elements, e.g., Health book, Optimized
						phonological description, Language survey; Anthropology field notes; also use topical words such
						as Tone; Verb structure; Kinship.</p>
					<p>Element should be repeated for multiple subject terms
						<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf --></p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>A Library of Congress subject heading:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:subject xsi:type="dcterms:LCSH"&gt;African
					languages&lt;/dc:subject&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
				<todo>
					<p>Geographic and temporal aspects of language varieties go in Coverage. Subject is where social
						dimensions of language varieties would go. Add an example.</p>
				</todo>
			</element>
			<element name="Title">
				<definition>A name given to the resource.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p>Typically, a Title will be a name by which the resource is formally known. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
					<p>A translation of the title can be supplied in a second Title element. Use the <i>lang</i>
						attribute to identify the language of these elements.</p>
					<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
					<p>[Can be] a name given to a work to identify it if a formal title is not used, such as for a data
						set or collection of texts. For a formal title, this is generally in the language in which the
						work is written or recorded. If the title is in a language different from the language
						identified in \md-lang, note the language of the title in the \titleLang field.</p>
				</comment>
				<refinements>
					<dl>
						<dt>alternative</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>Any form of the title used as a substitute or alternative to the formal title of the
								resource. Comment: This qualifier can include Title abbreviations as well as
								translations. </p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</refinements>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt/>
						<!-- Empty definition term. -->
						<dd>
							<!-- Move to <bp><p>? -->
							<p>The <i>refine</i> attribute may optionally be used for a single refinement supported by
									<cit>DC-Q</cit>. The value <i>alternative</i> indicates a form of the title that is
								used as a substitute or alternative to the formal title of the resource. This qualifier
								can include abbreviated titles as well as translations. </p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>Minimal best practice is that every record must have an instance of the Title element.</p>
					<p>Recommended best practice is that only one instance of Title, namely the original title, be
						unqualified. All others (e.g. translations) should be specified as the Alternative
					refinement.</p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>A typical title:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:title&gt;A Dictionary of the Nggela Language&lt;/dc:title&gt;</eg>
					<p>A vernacular title with translation:</p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:title xsi:type="olac:ISO639-3" olac:code="llu"&gt;Na tala 'uria na idulaa
						diana&lt;/dc:title&gt; &lt;dcterms:alternative xml:lang="eng" &gt;The road to
						good reading&lt;/dcterms:alternative&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
			</element>
			<!-- Type:   i Exhibited perhaps the most different archivespecific
      		interpretations of its use
      		i Evidence of different vocabularies for type used
      		by numerous archives
      		i When coded, the codes were generally applied
      		correctly
      		i Abused by some poor mappings -->
			<!-- iMore thorough best practice guidelines for:
      		– Description
      		– Identifier
      		– Rights
      		– Subject qualifiers and extensions (dealing with
      		overlap, use of multiple schemes)
      		– Type and its extensions
      		iThe definitions and controlled vocabularies
      		have to be in order FIRST -->
			<!-- http://www.language-archives.org/events/olac02/proceedings.pdf -->
			<element name="Type">
				<definition>The nature or genre of the resource.</definition>
				<comment>
					<p> Type includes terms describing general categories, functions, genres, or aggregation levels for
						content. To describe the physical or digital manifestation of the resource, use the
						<xref>Format</xref> element. <cit>DCMT</cit></p>
					<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
					<p>Select from the closed range of resource types; some have subtypes further specified. This
						relates to the intended use or mode of perception by a user, e.g., a computer image file of a
						text (such as a scanned document) is type 'text', not type 'image'. The list here contains all
						the DCMI:Type vocabulary terms and the terms of HIS: RMR_mode where those differ from
					DCMI:Type</p>
				</comment>
				<schemes>
					<dl>
						<dt>dcterms:DCMIType</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>A list of types used to categorize the nature or genre of the content of the resource.
									<cit>DCMI-Type</cit>.</p>
						</dd>
						<dt>olac:linguistic-type</dt>
						<dd>
							<p>The nature or genre of the content of the resource from a linguistic standpoint
									<cit>OLAC-Linguistic-Type</cit>. For a resource that is information in or about a
								language, use this scheme to identify what kind of information it is from a linguistic
								standpoint.</p>
							<!-- Following <p> from OLACSIL.txt -->
							<p>Linguistic Type extension of the Type element should only be used if a resource
								represents one of the structural types in the range set. The element may be repeated if
								a resource represents more than one linguistic type. So, for example, a primary text
								accompanied by a lexicon of vocabulary items would be described as both a primary text
								and a lexicon. In many cases, adequate description of a linguistic resource will require
								that the Linguistic Type extension be used in conjunction with the Discourse Type
								extension of the Type element, or the Linguistic extension of the Subject element. For
								example, a narrative text might be described as both a primary text (OLAC Linguistic
								Type) and a narrative (OLAC Discourse Type).</p>
						</dd>
					</dl>
				</schemes>
				<bp>
					<p>Minimal best practice is that every record contain at least one Type element that uses the
							<i>dcterms:DCMIType</i> scheme.</p>
					<p>When a resource is an instance of language data, documentation, or description, minimal best
						practice is to use the <i>olac:linguistic-type</i> scheme to identify its linguistic data type.
					</p>
				</bp>

				<examples>
					<p>The resource is a video
						recording:<!-- Is "video recording" really a Type and not Format (because 'photograph' was an example of Format according to Jung-ran Park.)? Need examples to contrast Format and Type. --></p>
					<eg>&lt;dc:type xsi:type="dcterms:DCMIType">MovingImage&lt;/cd:type&gt;</eg>
				</examples>
				<todo>
					<p>The following is leftover from 2002; do we still want it? For a resource that is a software tool,
						Type.linguistic identifies what kind of information it processes. Service providers may use this
						information to match data files with software tools that might be applied to them.</p>
				</todo>
			</element>
		</section>
	</body>
	<todo>
		<p>There is not yet a provision for handling subject categorization by linguistic (genetic) classification.</p>
		<p>Rights.software has been left in limbo. It may be possible to unify it with Rights.</p>
	</todo>
	<references>
		<ref abbrev="Copyright">Section 101, Definitions, Copyright Law of the United States of America and Related Laws
			Contained in Title 17 of the United States
				Code.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.loc.gov/copyright/title17/92chap1.html#101</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="DCMT">Dublin Core Metadata Terms.
			<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="DC-Q">Dublin Core
				Qualifiers.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/07/11/DCMT-qualifiers/</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="DCQ-HTML">Recording qualified Dublin Core metadata in HTML meta
				elements.<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/08/15/dcq-html/</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="DCMI-Registry">DCMI Open Metadata
				Registry.<br/>&lt;<url>http://wip.dublincore.org:8080/registry/Registry</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="DCMI-Submit">DCMI Open Metadata Registry: Submit a Scheme for
				Registration.<br/>&lt;<url>http://wip.dublincore.org:8080/registry/authServlet?req_type=newscheme&amp;lang=enUS</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="DCMI-Box">DCMI Box
				<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/2000/07/11/dcmi-type-vocabulary/</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="DCMI-Period">DCMI Period
			<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-period/</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="DCMI-Point">DCMI Point <br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-point/</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="DCMI-Type">DCMI Type Vocabulary.
				<br/>&lt;<url>http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-type-vocabulary/</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="IANA-CS">Internet Character Sets.<br/>
				&lt;<url>http://www.isi.edu/in-notes/iana/assignments/character-sets</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="IMT">IMT <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="ISO639-3">ISO 639: Codes for the representation of names of languages - Part 3: Alpha-3 code for
			comprehensive coverage of languages.<br/> &lt;<url>http://www.sil.org/iso639-3/</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="URI">URI <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2396.txt</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="MIME">Internet Media
				Types.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.isi.edu/in-notes/iana/assignments/media-types/media-types</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="OAI">Open Archives Initiative. <br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="OLAC-BP">Best Practice Recommendations for Language Resource
				Description.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/bpr.html</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="OLAC-Linguistic-Field">OLAC Linguistic Subject
				Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/field.htmll</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="OLAC-Linguistic-Type">OLAC Linguistic Data Type
				Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/REC/type.html</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="OLAC-Metadata">OLAC
			Metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/metadata.html</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="OLAC-Language">OLAC Language
			Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="OLAC-Role">OLAC Role
			Vocabulary.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/OLAC/???</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="TGN">Getty Thesaurus of Geographical
				Terms.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabulary/tgn/index.html</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="OLAC-WP">White Paper on Establishing an Infrastructure for Open Language
				Archiving<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.language-archives.org/docs/white-paper.html</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="W3CDTF">Date and Time Formats, W3C
			Note.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-datetime</url>&gt;</ref>

		<ref abbrev="OAI-DC">Schema for OAI implementation of Dublin Core
				metadata.<br/>&lt;<url>http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/1.1/dc.xsd</url>&gt;</ref>

	</references>
</OLAC_doc>
