<submissionPolicies>
<policy>
<repositoryName>Language Commons Language Corpora</repositoryName>
<link>languagecommons.org</link>
<text>
The Language Commons accepts linguistic corpora which may be
distributed under any of the licenses supported by the Internet
Archive.
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>Kaipuleohone</repositoryName>
<link>scholarspace.manoa.hawaii.edu</link>
<text>
ScholarSpace at the University of Hawaii at Manoa accepts submissions
of scholarly material from all members of the UH community. Submitters
must first get permission from the administrators by contacting us at
micro@hawaii.edu
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>CHILDES Data repository</repositoryName>
<link>childes.talkbank.org</link>
<text>
CHILDES and TalkBank happily accept archival submissions of transcript
corpora of conversational interactions. Interactions involving young
children are included in CHILDES. Interactions involving older
children and adults are included in TalkBank. Corpora are further
divided into collections by language and interest areas (aphasia,
bilingualism, classroom, legal, etc.). All corpora must eventually be
entered in CHAT format and must pass through XML validation of this
format. In many cases, we are willing to work with contributors to
reformat their data into CHAT. Because this formatting can involve
significant work on our part, we place a priority on contributions
that include audio or video materials. However, we are interested in
including non-linked materials and materials without media when the
corpora themselves are intrinsically interesting. Guidelines for
contribution can be found at http://talkbank.org/share.
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>The Rosetta Project: A Long Now Foundation
            Library of Human Language</repositoryName>
<link>rosettaproject.org</link>
<text>
The Rosetta Project accepts a wide variety of materials that help
document the languages of the world. If you would like to help build
this open public collection through materials you have assembled or
created, please contact rosetta@longnow.org and tell us more about
them.
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>TALKBANK Data repository</repositoryName>
<link>talkbank.org</link>
<text>
CHILDES and TalkBank happily accept archival submissions of transcript
corpora of conversational interactions. Interactions involving young
children are included in CHILDES. Interactions involving older
children and adults are included in TalkBank. Corpora are further
divided into collections by language and interest areas (aphasia,
bilingualism, classroom, legal, etc.). All corpora must eventually be
entered in CHAT format and must pass through XML validation of this
format. In many cases, we are willing to work with contributors to
reformat their data into CHAT. Because this formatting can involve
significant work on our part, we place a priority on contributions
that include audio or video materials. However, we are interested in
including non-linked materials and materials without media when the
corpora themselves are intrinsically interesting. Guidelines for
contribution can be found at http://talkbank.org/share.
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>SIL Language and Culture Archives</repositoryName>
<link>sil.org</link>
<text>
The SIL International Language and Culture Archives accepts
submissions from active and retired SIL staff in the areas of language
and culture documentation and description, and language development.
Under some circumstances, the Archives will also accept materials from
former staff and persons more casually associated with SIL language
work, if such materials relate to research done with the assistance of
SIL or its staff, and there is not a more appropriate institution able
to accept and curate the materials long-term. Please address any
questions to the Archives by sending email to archive_dallas AT
sil.org.
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>Language Documentation and Conservation</repositoryName>
<link>ldc.scholarspace.manoa.hawaii.edu</link>
<text>
ScholarSpace at the University of Hawaii at Manoa accepts submissions
of scholarly material from all members of the UH community. Submitters
must first get permission from the administrators by contacting us at
micro@hawaii.edu
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>LINDAT/CLARIAH-CZ digital library at the Institute of Formal and Applied Linguistics (ÚFAL), Faculty of Mathematics and Physics, Charles University</repositoryName>
<link>lindat.mff.cuni.cz</link>
<text>
https://lindat.mff.cuni.cz/repository/xmlui/page/about
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>Archive of the Indigenous Languages of Latin America (AILLA)</repositoryName>
<link>ailla.utexas.org</link>
<text>
AILLA welcomes any legitimate materials in or about the indigenous
languages of Latin America. Legitimate materials are those produced by
or in collaboration with native speakers of those languages. For more
information see the "Information for Depositors" page
(http://www.ailla.utexas.org/site/dep_info.html).
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>The Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project (SLAAP)</repositoryName>
<link>ncslaap.lib.ncsu.edu</link>
<text>
SLAAP is constantly adding new recording collections. If you are
interested in the possibility of adding your data to the archive
please contact the archive administrator.
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>Slovenian language resource repository CLARIN.SI</repositoryName>
<link>clarin.si</link>
<text>
https://www.clarin.si/repository/xmlui/page/about
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>Webonary Sites</repositoryName>
<link>webonary.org</link>
<text>
Any one who agrees with the terms of service published on the website
may submit a dictionary produced with FLEx for publication by
Webonary.
</text>
</policy>
<policy>
<repositoryName>Eurac Research CLARIN Centre</repositoryName>
<link>clarin.eurac.edu</link>
<text>
https://clarin.eurac.edu/repository/xmlui/page/about
</text>
</policy>
</submissionPolicies>
